<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon declaringe hovv vue [sic] are iustified by faith</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1549</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 110 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11925</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22238</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104732</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840465</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840465</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4974</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11925)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4974)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 146:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon declaringe hovv vue [sic] are iustified by faith</title>
                  <author>E. T.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[118] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Willia[m] hyl at the signe of ye grene hyl, and there to be soulde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at londun :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1549?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Translated out of French by E.T." (leaf A1v).</note>
                  <note>Publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A [2d]A-F (-A1) G⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4974:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4974:1"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>A Sermon declaringe hovv vue at Iuſtified by faith</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Imprinted at londun by Willia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hyl at the ſigne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grene hyl, and there to be ſoulde</p>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:4974:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>VVHAT IT Is TOO BE:</hi> iuſtifyed by Chriſte and the way howe we are iuſtifyed and reprouing errour concernig it. Tranſlated out of latin into Englyſhe by E. T.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>or aſmuch as iuſtificacion whiche we haue throughe chriſte ys moſte propre to a Chryſtyan man, and is the well ſpring of al other gifts, vertuous and goodnes, yt ſhalbe meete firſt to ſe what we call to be iuſtified by chryſt or to be iuſte through chriſt, That we mai geue thankes to god the father &amp; chriſt our lorde for his greate giftes firſt god doth not iuſtifie or abſolute the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> giltie or pronounce him iuſt (for thus ſingni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fiethe iuſtifie) as a Tyraunte is wonte to doo whoo when he heareth one of his gard accuſed be he neuer ſo miſcheuous he defendeth him, excuſeth him: and wil not haue hym accompted gyltie, be his myſchefe neuerſo manifeſt and ſo he iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth him neither puniſheth him acor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge
<pb facs="tcp:4974:2"/> to his deſertes, rather he wyll haue him accompted as a goode iuſte and honeſt parſone the which maner of iuſtifyinge is deceytfull<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wycked, and tyranny called. But god doth iuſtefy y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſinner after this ſorte. For as he is iuſt ſo is his iudgment rightuous. As Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uid witneſſeth. Lord thou art iuſte, and thy iudgemente is rightuous. For the which cauſe he fauoreth vs, not whyles we ſinne, neyther accompteth vs a iuſt whyles we are in ſinne, nether alloweth ſynners as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Tyranne doth. But yee God nether doth iuſtify men as a good kynge dothe for it is the part of a good Prince when an innocente and gyltles parſon is in ieopardy to defende hys innocencye againſt falſe accuſacions &amp; openly to pronounce him his iuſte and ſet him free as he deſerueth to be. But yet neyther after thys ſorte, we can bee iuſtified as gyltles. For we are by natu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re ſinners. There are that wyl forgeue the faultes and pardon hym for none o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther cauſe but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are ſory for theyr
<pb facs="tcp:4974:3"/> euyll deade neyther do require hym to ſatiſfye, but delyuer hym freelye. But god dothe not ſo iuſtefy the ſynner not becauſe he can not but becauſe ſo it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>methe goode to hym to forgiue noman with oute ſatyſfactyon as after ſhalbe declared. Neither are we therfore Iuſtyfyede becauſe we canne geue GOD anye thinge of oure owne to counterpaiſe owre curſes and ſynnes. For there is nothinge in man that can ſatiſfye before god for the leaſte ſynne yea man is not worthye to obtayne the leſte droppe of mercye at gods hand as Iacob ſaythe to god in geneſis, I am leſſe then al thi mercies for as ſambros ſaye the the redempcion of chriſts blo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ude ſhulde waxe vile. Neither the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue of mans goode workes wold neue place to the mercye of god, if iuſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fication, whiche is freely geuen, were<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done to workes that went before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſhuld not be a free gift of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> geuer but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wage &amp; rewarde of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worker as ſpaule crieth if we are iuſtified by the workes
<pb facs="tcp:4974:3"/> of the lawe then is CHRIST deade in vaine neither can we ſaie this truly that we are made iuſte partly by the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſfaction of chriſt &amp; partly by our own for ſo we myghte boaſte of oure ſelues whiche is contrarye to S, paules doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine. For he ſaith he that dothe glorye let him glorye in god. And howe often dothe all the ſcrypture warne to geue god al honor &amp; glory of iuſtifing ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by faythe no regarde had of oure merytes I wyll tell the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> truthe plainlye yf the leaſte iote of oure iuſtificacion hong of oure ſelues the promes of God were not true. As S. Paule wytneſſethe in hys epyſtle to the Romaynes byſydes that as Agath the Prophete and paule the apoſtle wryte, all thoſe thynges are fylthie and vncleane that the vncleane goo about or doe, but al thoſe are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane whoeſoeuer they be that are not iuſtified of god, wherfore theyr mercyes can not pleaſe God ne appeaſe hys wrathe by anye meanes This eſaye wil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling
<pb facs="tcp:4974:4"/> to declare compareth all our owne righteouſnes to a clothe defiled wythe womens flowres, And ſ. Auſten affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mith that all the deſeruynges of men wer loſt in adam after he had tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed and doonne that ſynne whereby we were al condemned and made voide of righteouſnes. For by Adam we are all deade but bi Chriſte we are referred to lyfe. Therefore good bretherne weighe with me how that a man can of himſelf redeme and paie ranſome for ſo greate ſynnes: that is to wit how he being dea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de can reſtoore him ſelfe to life agayne for this cauſe Chryſte ſayde not the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of the Synagooge thou ſhalte ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatyſfye for parte, and I wyll fullfyll that that thou canne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſte not. But he ſayde to hym onelye beleue. And haue a ſure confydence. Paule in the, Epyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to the. Romans. Ad. Galat. Dothe proue that no man Is Iuſtyfyed ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the Lawe of vertuous lyuinge neyther by mannes iuſtyce yea rather
<pb facs="tcp:4974:4"/> mannes iuſtice did crucifie Chryſte by the Iewes and condemne him before ponce pylate and did perſecute, trouble and torment the ſame Chriſt diuerſlye but Saule after called paule in his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bres. But I praye you when hath ſuch a iuſtice as can make men iuſte and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed. Fyrſt after paule the lawe, dothe en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>creaſe ſinne &amp; dothe not take it awaye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe dothe bynde and condempne and not looſe and ſett tree, yt kyllethe and not quickneth, Moreouer the phareſee did pronunce him ſelfe partlye bye him ſelfe and partlye bye god, and therfore he gaue god thankes, but bycauſe he gaue not the whole glorye to god, and to him ſelfe ignoraunce, as the publica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did, he was not iuſtifyed. Let vs cal to remembraunce the parable of the ſhepe herde that leauynge the xcix. Shepes whiche me anethe then that will iuſtify<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fye them ſelues) dyd ſeke, and fynde that ſhepe that was ſoſte and brought hyr to hyr Foulde. Bye the Whyche
<pb facs="tcp:4974:5"/> thinge are ment ſynners, that acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege there ſynnes and truſt to be ſaued and made iuſte onely by the mercye and bountefullnes of god there is in certain cytyes &amp; contreys a lawe or cuſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be that in the laſt weke of lent we call the paſſion weke certaine theues &amp; priſoners are delyuered &amp; let out of pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paying no fyne by no dede of ther ow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> only mere mercy of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prices w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cuſtome I do not trye out in this place whether it be good or badde. The cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencye of princes I prayſe if they haue anye ſuperſtycion therin y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I diſrpaiſe. This fact doth expreſſe vnto vs liuelye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goodnes of god for as thoſe priſoners are delyuered wher as they deſerued no ſuch thing but rather extrem pu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blably ar we ſaued by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mercy of god only chriſt bei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g our mediator &amp; aduocat wil ye be aſſured y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this is ſo marke the thefe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was hanged not for fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chriſt tel me what good did he at anye time why Chriſt ſhoulde ſaye vnto him this daye thou ſhalte be wyth me in parradyce
<pb facs="tcp:4974:5"/> he was ſcourged ye wil ſaye he was tor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mented and hownge on the croſſe I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere that he deſerued for his meſchefe not onely thoſe but greater yea euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>inge death for by thoſe puniſhementes happelye he might ſatiſfye mans lawe yet al his paynes were neuer able to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terpaiſe GODS iuſtice if he had ben put to death a thouſande times if anye obiect that that was done by a wonder and by a ſpeciall preuillege withe them I will ſaye that all thoſe that are ſaued are ſaued by a lytle mirracle and by the mere mercye of GOD for ſomuche as it is euedent that one manne is not bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter then an other by natur but by grace for by nature we are all equall in daun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gier of euerlaſtynge dampnatyon. And as Sayncte Paule Callethe vs the Chylderne of Wrathe.</p>
            <p>But the ryche, the Lorde GOD by hys greate mercye dyd choyſe whoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me he would haue before the begyuning &amp; creatyon, of the Woorlde, &amp; whome he
<pb facs="tcp:4974:6"/> dyd chewſe them he called, whom he cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led them he iuſtified, whome he iuſtified them he glorified. This ſaying is none of myne but of Paules the a poſtle ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our iuſtificacion, our ſaluacion &amp; our bleſſednes are al wholye to be grun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded in Chriſt, and we partly i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſte &amp; partly in our ſelues for the which cauſe Paul taught y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Corinthians y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no man can laye any other foundacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beſides y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is laide i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ieſu Chriſt whoſoeuer they be that ſtable y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ther ſal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on any other the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him they ar not wiſe ne experte in heuenly thinges, as y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which bulde not vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſuer rocke, but on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lowſe ſand which howſe is not able to ſtande when any tempeſt of wynd or of greate floud of the ſea ſhal aſſayle it as our ſauiour Chriſt teacheth the gala<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which bei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g deceayued by falſe ꝓ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes did chalenge to be ſaued partlie by their oune meritis, partly by chriſtes which there opinion Paul can not beare i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no wiſe, but doth exagite it as peſtife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, &amp; derogatine from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glorie of God
<pb facs="tcp:4974:6"/> for loke how muche ye geue to Mannes merites (co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g iuſtification) be they neuer ſo good &amp; holy, ſo much ye take a way from the glory of god, and ſo much is plucked fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of chriſt as is put to the merites of man wherfore no man oght to thinke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is made iuſt becauſe he ſatiſfieth god him ſelfe either in part or whole It is alſo an errour y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> certe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaie the workes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goo before iuſtificacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> although they be not good of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues yet to pleaſe god through Chriſt and to be compted of him as merites, whereon they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they are iuſtified by chriſt as withoute whome thoſe workes were voyde &amp; in vayne. To them I aunſwer that this workes are ſynne and wy firſt an euel tree can not bringe forthe good frutes. Secondarelye becauſe without faithe and a ſure truſte in the merite of God exhibited for, Chriſte no man can pleaſe god. And paule alſo counteth the gay workes the iuſtice of the law which he had don before his iuſtification as a hurt and a vile thynge. And wryttynge
<pb facs="tcp:4974:7"/> to Thimothe doth teache that we were ſaued before the worlde through Chriſt not accordinge to our deſeruinges but to his prepenſed wyll and grace. To the which ſaying Auſten ſtucke ſtoutlye as his workes do witnes, who then wyl ſay that ſinne dothe pleaſe the ryghtuouſe God and that they for Chriſtes ſake are reputed as merites that ſo ſynne maye make ſatiffaction for ſinne? Chriſt died for oure ſinnes not to allowe them but to emproue and dampne them), and too teache that nothing do the diſpleaſe him but ſinne But they ſaye to them that lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue God all thinges are good. It is true: but how do they loue God who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me they knowe not? As yet not redemed to god through faith and borne ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>allye as yet not lyghtened with his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſprite as yeat not delyuered from the pryſon of darkeneſſe and grafted in the kyngdome of his beloued and gracious ſonne of God. And the place of Paull is not to be vnderſtand of ſinne but of the croſſe and afflictions as thoſe thinges
<pb facs="tcp:4974:7"/> that go before and the folowing of the place declare the the more a worthye iuſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyce of god that ſhall not onlye not con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demne ſynne but take it for vertue &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> well rewarded let the opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſo abſurd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and wicked befarre both from the harte &amp; the mouth of Chriſten men,</p>
            <p>Laſtelye ſome men woulde thinke that we are iuſtifyed by Chryſte as by an aduocat meane or enterceſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he obteyneth of his father for vs remiſſion of ſynnes whych we do not denye howe be it thei that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſaye neither nothynge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne all that in the thynge is to be ſayde for thes thinges that be of greater wei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ght the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thes be thei y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> paſſe ouer for firſt chriſt did take vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſynnes of his and wold haue attributed to him (ſuch was his greate loue towarde vs his fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther agreinne to it, yea wyllynge ſo to be whiche Eſayas ſaw longe or it came moreouer he not onelye toke them to hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe but as thoughe he had done them ſelfe whoe yet onelye and nomore but he was wyth oute all ſpotte of ſynne
<pb facs="tcp:4974:8"/> wold pay our rau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt bitter kid of deth wherbi he fully co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trepeſed &amp; ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fied y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> iuſtice, nether therw<hi rend="sup">t</hi> conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t he ga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue vs his innocency, righteouſnes boli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; wyſdom &amp;, which is aboue all this gaue vs his ſprit, that therby we being quickened not with our owne ſprite but with the ſprite of Chryſte &amp; that we new borne ye truylye borne agayn myght cal rightly God ye father and ſtand before him w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out feare although we had neuer bene defiled with the leaſt ſpot of ſinne For he that ſpared not his own Sonne but gaue him for vs how can it bee that he wyll not geue vs all thinges wyth hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Nowe therfore we are iuſte without ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne gyltles and innocentes, not onely by our owne rightuouſnes that we are w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſinne for Chriſte hath our ſinne vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pon him and made it hys and hath van<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quiſed it by his deathe but alſoo by the rightuouſneſſe of Chriſte &amp; the purite which he hath geuen vs mooſte aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly, wherw<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we beinge wel cled and adorned maye boldly apere before god
<pb facs="tcp:4974:8"/> this heauenly giftes theſe vertues theſe heuenle and eternal treaſures only fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the, and ſure perſuaſyon of the mercye of God conteynethe in it and the bygger the faith is the greater alſo are they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temed by fayth all other giftes are mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſured, fayethe is the righteouſnes of a Chriſten man, fayth is the iuſtify catyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> This is it that we cal to be iuſtified by Chriſt the whiche he that hathe truly at<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayned, theye haue attayned it all that with all their harte put theyr whole con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fydence and truſte in Chriſt he maye tru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye ſaye withe. Paule I am crucyfyed withe Chriſte yet I lyue not nowe but Chriſt in me what nede I holde you lon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger withe more wordes. He that thus is iuſtified maye ſtande before the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeate of God with as good a coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tenaunce with as like fauour as Chriſt him ſelf for there is like ſtate of the hed and other membres. For whoe dare ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther accuſe or condemne them that God hath choſen them that god hath promy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed iuſt and for whome Chriſte is medy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ator
<pb facs="tcp:4974:9"/> and interceſſour. They are clothed with Chriſte and all his garmentes wherfore as Iaacob pleaſed his father in Eſau his ſteade ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g on Eſau his clothes Semblably wyll ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke vs for no, true ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes clothed with the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt and wyl geue vs the enheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce of his heauenlye kingdome. with Ieſu Chriſt hys ſonne to whome be all honor and glory for euer and euer</p>
            <closer>Amen</closer>
            <trailer>Finis</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4974:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ To the right worſhipfull and his ſinguler good Maſter Silueſter, But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, George Bancrafte, Wiſhethe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitye and healthe, boeth of bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye and ſoule.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I conſidered wyth my ſelfe the greate &amp; dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, abuſes in the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtracion of ſuch ſacramentes as our ſauiour Ieſus Chriſte left to his miſticall bodie the churche of the fayethfull, to be externe ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and tokens of ſuche giftes as God hath, and doth dailie worcke in vs, to his own glorie, and ſalua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion of oure ſoules<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I can fynde, perceiue, and proue none to be ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche abuſed, as the holy and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret ſupper of our Lord. For wher as he ordined, that holy ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his bodie, and bloud to be eaten and dronken in remembraunce of his paſſion whoſe frute they taſte therin, which haue ther ſtedfaſte fayth in hym. And thereby ſhewe
<pb facs="tcp:4974:10"/> furth the Lordes death vntyll he come, and as brede is made, of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny graines, &amp; wyne of many gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, ſo the membres of the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacion of Chriſtes churche. Haue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge one God, one fayeth, and one Baptiſme, are put in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in eateinge and drinkinge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are one bodie, whereof Chriſte is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hed. The beally biſhopes of Ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bilon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romiſhe Antichriſt, haue anullyd extripate, &amp; cleane abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ordinaunce of Chriſt and vſe of thappoſtelles, in the admini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtracion therof. And haue of their owne brayne excogitated deuiſed and brought in to the churche a newe, and ſtraynge ordinaunce for the ſame, whiche is as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie to chriſtes wil and purpoſe, touch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing that bleſſed ſupper as heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to earth, lyght to darknes, lyfe to death, and they call it the bleſſyd Maſſe but it maye be truely cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyd a dilueſh Maſking, for menes
<pb facs="tcp:4974:10"/> eies, are maſked there with y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei cannot ſe the trueth, but through that deteſtable abominacion haue bene, brought to moſte miſerable perdicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for they applie it to ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyoures in war for faire weather and rayne for the plage pockes and ſuche other diſeaſes for bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes ſicke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morren for preſerua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion of health, and for remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſynnes, boeth for the quicke and deade I wyl not, ſpeake how God is mocked therin and Chriſte had in deriſion they pley booe pepe, wyth ſeſte me, or ſeſte me not. My pene abhoreth to write what duc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge knellenge lickinge kiſſing or Croſſing and breathing theſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilles apes haue deuiſed in thys whoriſhe Maſſe ther deſguiſinge In apparell at Maſſe hath pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked manye a pore mannes purs and hath robbid theire ſoules of the true frutes of the ſpirite, for al ſuche ſomes of monie that men
<pb facs="tcp:4974:11"/> ſhoulde haue beſtowed on theire poure parentes, childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and nedie neighbours was to litle for their veſtime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes albes, ſtoles chalices, corporaces, aulter clothes, Maſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bockes, and ſuche other, wherein Chriſte hath no delite for Chriſte and the Appoſtelles vſede none ſuche diſguiſynge in the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtracion of thys bleſſid Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſtes bodie and bloud but were contendid with ſuch ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mente as they were accuſtomed daylye to were &amp; ſo theſe ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les Idolaters, ſhewing them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues of what generacion they are, dare ſo bouldlye face out ſuch ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifeſte lyes agaynſte gods glorye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> plaine truth, and ordinaunce of chriſt What ſhal I ſpeake of theſe holi mumers (I would haue ſaied holy Maſſe mongers) that whan they here of any rich manes death they flocke together lyke rauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to a dead Carre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte
<pb facs="tcp:4974:11"/> them that mourne for the deade wyth hope of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſurrection of the fleſhe, not to gyue thankes to God for them that are depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the fayeth of Chriſte nor to praye that we, departinge in the ſame fayeth maye wyth them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue like rewarde but to get mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney with Requiem eterna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and pro quorum memoria corpus Chriſti ſumitur with cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing daſhing of holy water, &amp; ſuch other lyke Iuglinges ſo that the ryght vſe of it is cleane altered as thought chriſt had neuer ordeined it in remembraunce of his death and paſſion and for as much as in thys treatiſe folowinge the true vſe of the Lordes ſupper and alſo the deueliſhe patchinge of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhe Maſſe is in fewe wordes li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uely declared I haue thought it good to tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlate the ſame into the engliſhe tonge to the edifinge of my dere bretherne in Chriſt prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge God the father of oure ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
<pb facs="tcp:4974:12"/> Ieſus Chriſt, that theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges may ſhortlie be reformed that the pore flocke of Chriſt be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more deceyuede wyth ſuche craftye conueiaunce to kepe them in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenual blinded for lucres ſake, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great daunger of their ſoules and pernicious dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of gods glorie to whome be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye for euer</p>
            <closer>AMEN</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:4974:12"/>
            <p>FOr aſmuche as God hath commaunded vs by his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <note place="margin">i. Pet. iii.</note> Peter (Oh ye fathers of oure countrie) in wyſdome gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uitie and godlines to be readie at all tymes to gyue an anſwere to euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that aſketh vs a reſon of oure fayth it is mete y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhould more gladly anſwere to a queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proponed beinge requirede of you oure moſte Soueraigne Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates to whome we knowe alſo what is oure dutie in other thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. We haue affirmed and vpon ſure grounde, and reaſon proued, in oure publike ſermons, that the popiſhe Maſſe, is not an offering for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quicke and dead but a moſte deteſtable abominacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before god And therfore a man wyll not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyue how glad we are, which loue the truthe, that you oure moſte prudent ſenatours require of vs an anſwer to thys queſtion for we conceyue greate hope that God
<pb facs="tcp:4974:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4974:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4974:14"/> whyche moueth you to deſire to atteine the knowledge of the light and truth, wil of his infinite mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cye encreſe hys grace in you that after the example of the god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye kinges, Ezechias and Iolias when the trueth diligently ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched out and truly knowen, you wyl take awaye, aboliſhe and vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlye diſtroye all ſuch tradicions of man as are repugnante to the worde of God. And al ſuche thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges as are taught and ſet fourth contrarie to the ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of god and holſome doctrine of Chriſte, whiche thinges ſtire vp the anger and griuouſe diſpleaſure for God agaynſte vs miſerable creatures for in ſo doinge, you ſhall noriſhe confirme and eſtabliſhe peace vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and concorde in thys noble ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Baſell, and bringe your ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iectes to a ſincere &amp; godly fourme of lyuinge, that at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daie of Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement the bloud and condemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacion
<pb facs="tcp:4974:14"/> of moſte deteſtable ſinners ſhall not be required at your han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des being oure Magiſtrates and gouerners but rather you ſhalbe rewarded of God and receyue in thys worlde prayſe and glorye boeth of your ſubiectes &amp; of ſtrain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gers for nothinge can rather win the fauoure of ſubiectes to their Maieſtrates and rulers &amp; bringe them to obedience then the worde of God, and his commaundemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes frelye preachede and wythout daunger of poniſhement, as you may euidently perceyue by Ioſue <note place="margin">Ioſ. i.</note> and the people of God committed to hys gouernaunce. And ſtrayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers are moued wyth nothynge ſo much as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther ſe the truth, the glorie of god and an honeſte or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der of lyuinge magnified &amp; had in reuerence, for God doeth kepe the citie that ſeketh his glorie.</p>
            <p>Fyrſte of all we proteſte that in our puklyke ſermones and in thys
<pb facs="tcp:4974:15"/> writynge we not here ſpeake nor write againſt the moſt holye ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Chriſt or the Apoſtles in the adminiſtracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lordes ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per, but we both ſpeake &amp; write a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> abuſes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be crept into the church, &amp; are obſtinatli defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, bi co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of time w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hollie ſcriptures, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great hinderau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the fruites of chriſtes paſſion &amp; craftie deceiueinge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnlerned people co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie to Chriſtes ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; adminiſtracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon rumor is through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mali<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciouſe enuie, &amp; faulſe forgid lies of ſome popiſh preachers &amp; of ſome o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are euen againſt vs which know y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we goo about to let aboliſhe, and bringe to nought all good workes, they fayne this on ther owne heade, as they do al other thynges for nothynge, can be more greauouſe to vs then, to here that men do not lyue after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dementes of God. And we
<pb facs="tcp:4974:15"/> know through the grace of God. What ceremonies, &amp; what pert of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cerimonies is profitable &amp; mete for chriſten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; our purpoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a good conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is to vſe well ſincerly, &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out any faulſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deuiſed tracions, ſo muche of this ſacrament of oure Lordes ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per, as was moſt perfectly begon, and ordiened of Chriſt our maſter and there can no man proue that our intent was other wiſe at any time and thys by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aſſiſtaunce of gods grace, we wil affirme by the onely ſcriptures of God. Now we wil in godes name declar &amp; ſhewe furth our reaſones for this queſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on proponed. Vndoubtely al ſuch as do not regard &amp; care for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> only glory of god teach nothing that is godly, true, or in aniwiſe profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. <note place="margin">Math. ii.</note> For god ſaith by Malachi. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophet. And now, Oh ye prieſtes this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t toucheth you if you wil not heare it nor regard it
<pb facs="tcp:4974:16"/> my name, ſayeth the Lorde, of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes I wyll ſende accurſſe vppon you, and wil Curſſe your bleſſing yea curſſe them wil I if ye do not take hede It is therfore manifeſt that God beynge griuouſely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed curſſeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that regarde not his name and glorie, for God is gellouſe and a conſuming fier. He wil haue hys name magnified <note place="margin">Deut. v.</note> and prayeſid the Iues and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles dyd fall into lewde myndes <note place="margin">Rom, i.</note> and corrupte Iudgementes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they knewe God, and dyd not glorifi him as God. The lord <note place="margin">Eſa. i. 42</note> hym ſelfe ſayeth, I wyll geue my glorye to none other. Finallye <note place="margin">Math, 12.</note> he that ſeketh not goddes glorye doeth nother deſire to encreaſe it nor doeth ſpeake, lyue, nor is of God but is adomination before God. For whoſoeuer is not wyth <note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.</note> Chriſt as who ſayth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God may be glorified, he is abominacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before God and is hys enemye when the <note place="margin">Eſai. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:4974:16"/> naturall man perceyueth not the thynges that pertayne to the <note place="margin">Ro. xi.</note> ſpirite of God. And hys thought is as fare in ſunder, from the wyl of God, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for in dede man touchinge hys owne knowledge, doeth knowe nothing leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyl of God. Who ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">Luc, xvi.</note> can tell what is the wyll of God and hys true glorye Chriſte ſayeth, that whiche is highly eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mede, amonge men is abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion before God, for men are euer prone and readye to fall and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the truth, to folowe &amp; cleaue to there owne profite, and inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions whereof Idolatrie &amp; othere abominacions, come vp and haue <note place="margin">Proue. iii.</note> there begynynge, wherefore the wiſe man ſayth, truſte in the lord <note place="margin">Deut. xii.</note> wyth all thyne herte, and not in thyne owne, wiſdome. And Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſayth, you ſhall not do after al thinges that we do here this day eueri ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what ſemeth hym good
<pb facs="tcp:4974:17"/> in his owne eies, it is therefore fo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liſhely ſpoken to ſaye, what thing ſoeuer that a man doeth for gods ſake is a good worke, and worthey to be rewarded, for then eueri ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> myght haue knoledge ſufficientli without any teaching or doctrine of the worde of God. But howe ſhoulde a man be then of an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubting co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience or wyth what hope, myght a man lyue to pleaſe God. Wher the knoledge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyl of God wantethe, there moſte alſo hope and fayeth want, namely in trouble and afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what ſo euer truely is not of fayeth is ſinne where Syne is there is abomina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on before God. Therfore god hath declared hys wyll and mynd, by thapoſtles. And Chriſte hym ſelfe (that our knowledge may be ſure, and our oppinion vndoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) howe god ought to be truely worſhiped. Moreouer he hath gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs aſtrayght co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to
<pb facs="tcp:4974:17"/> kepe his law, that we ſhal tourne nother to the right nor yet to the <note place="margin">Deut. xviii.</note> laſte hande that we ſhall nother adde nor take awaye any thynge from it, he that wyll not herken to the prophet that I wil raiſe vp ſayeth the Lorde, I wyl require it of hym, after the lawe was gyuen and the trueth was knowen, God would be worſhipped, as his word teacheth and the offence was the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> much more greuouſe. Albeit king Saull dyd kyll and offer fat Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, <note place="margin">i. R. xv.</note> to the true liuing God whiche was a good worke in apparau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: yet becauſe the ſcripture of God dyd not teache hym ſo to do, God therfore was griuoſlye diſpleaſed wyth hym. For althoughe he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered his ſacrifice to God, yet that acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted he to him for Idolatrie. <note place="margin">ii. Re. vi.</note> Oza died ſodenly becauſe he tuch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the arke againſte the Lordes commaundement, yet he thought it had ben a good dede. Dyd not
<pb facs="tcp:4974:18"/> the earth ſwallowe vp Corah and his adhere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes becauſe thei would <note place="margin">Nume. xvi.</note> take vppon them the office of the prieſts. The Iſrahelites, did think it a godlye and goodlye thynge to <note place="margin">Deut. xvi.</note> haue pleaſant groues night vnto the aulter of God, but hym dyd it not pleaſe. Thei though it a good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly facte at Tophet in Ieruſalem, <note place="margin">Ierome. vii.</note> to kyl and offer ther owne ſonnes but the more they did ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greater was ther abominacion before god For god ſayth he neuer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded them nether came it euer into his thought. God commaunded Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue <note place="margin">Ioſe. i.</note> to be ſtronge and bolde, that he myght obſerue, and do accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to al the lawe, which Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes commaundyd hym, and that he ſhould turne ther from, nither to the ryght nor to the lefte ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he myght do wiſely in al thynges <note place="margin">Eſa. xxx.</note> he toke in hande, god by hys pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Eſaias ſaith, alas for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient children, that wyll take
<pb facs="tcp:4974:18"/> counſayle wythout me and wyll take, aſecerete aduiſe, and not out of my ſpirite, therefore adde they ſinne vnto ſinne, and Chriſt ſaith <note place="margin">Math. vi.</note> in vaine do they ſerue me, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge the doctrines and preceptes of men, the proude herted Iewes did ſtande ſo well in there owne conceite for their tradicions and inuentions, that for loue thei had to them, they diſpiſed hated, and at laſt killide oure maiſter Chriſt <note place="margin">Iohn. xxi.</note> our aduerſaris dare ſaye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt and the apoſtles taught manye thynges, whyche are not wryten in the ſcripture, and that Chriſte ſayed hys Diſciples coulde not beare awaie al that he had taught thys cauil repungnau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the true vnderſtandinge of the ſcripture maye be an occaſion, and cauſe of greate errours for there wyth all lyes and heriſies maye be confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med they will ſaye albeit it is not written, yet the appoſtles taught
<pb facs="tcp:4974:19"/> it by worde of mouth, and alſo the ſcriptures of God, ſhoulde be an vnperfecte doctrine, which thyng to off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne, is blaſphemie agaynſte the holy goſt conſidering that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine of our fayth ſhould be put in queſtion. Therefore ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo muche is contayned in holye ſcripture as is neceſſary vnto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion to eueri one that beleueth They ſaye coulde the churche erre ſo longe time as it hath? If youre doctrnie be true the, true churche hath not errede, whiche hath the word of god only. The church ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely muſt be tried by the worde of God and not the worde of god by the churche whether the churche that beleueth be of manye or of fewe, for the churche is knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the frutes, and not becauſe, it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth of many, and hath her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynynge of the worde of God, and her frutes, are tried by the worde, whether the true chriſtan
<pb facs="tcp:4974:19"/> churche brought them forth or no if it be the true chriſten churche <note place="margin">Iohn. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſhe heareth no nother voice but Chriſtes her ſhepherde and bryd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grome, whiche the appoſtles prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to the church, and if an angel came out of heauen teaching any other doctrine then thys, let hym <note place="margin">Gala. i.</note> be accurſſed, if we loue and folow the doctrine that Chriſte taught and beinge hys diſciples, we ſhal not be excluded, frome the true churche ſo longe as we kepe wyth vs the worde of God. But he is puffed vp wyth pryde and doeth <note place="margin">i. Timo. vi.</note> knowe nothinge at al that wil not obey the word of God, he therfore which doth knowe nothinge, can not teache vs religion, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true worſhippinge of god, if the Maſſe be vſede as it hath ben hitherto, it can in no wyſe agree wyth the worde of God, but is ſo muche re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnaunt as what thing is moſt. The Maſſe therfore is a diuiliſhe
<pb facs="tcp:4974:20"/> Idolatrie, and deteſtable abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacion, againſt God, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teners therof, ſhal incurre, his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure for euer thys thyng we wil proue two waies firſt becauſe the popiſhe Maſſe, is vſed in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge lyke the ſupper that Chriſt ordeined, and differeth noleſſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it then blacke to white they ſynne therefore ſo griuouſlye as dyd A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chas y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> made an aultar at Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem <note place="margin">iii. Regu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. xvi.</note> lyke that which was at Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and caſte the aultare of god out of the temple ſo they haue, leſt the true vſe of oure Lordes ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, And in ſtede of it haue inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted and ordeinede the Maſſe of theyr owne foliſhe deuiſe, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion which is a great and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemouſe abominacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before god Moreouer we wyll proue by ther erroures and abuſinge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe, whyche they call an offeringe for the quicke and deade, that it is an horible abominacion, for if the
<pb facs="tcp:4974:20"/> Maſſe were ordeined of Chriſte, which is faulſe yet by there abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinge of it they woulde make it a blaſphemouſe, &amp; heinous abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacion before god, vndoubtedly we ought to folowe truely, and ſencelye, that thynge whiche is ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſolutly <note place="margin">Deut. vi.</note> ſufficient of it ſelfe alredie</p>
            <p>Firſte let vs conſyder and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pende the maner and order that Chriſte vſed at the inſtitucion of thys holly and ſacrete ſupper, and then we wyll confer the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the truth. But we ought to learne all theſe thynges of the Euangeliſtes, and of Saynte Paule, and of none other. Verely the true Maſſe, which is worthy al kindes of praieſes, is the Maſſe which Chriſte ordeyned, at hys laſte ſupper before he ſhoulde ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fere, <note place="margin">Luk, xxii.</note> for when the houre was come, he ſate downe and the twelue appoſtles wyth hym, and he ſayed vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I haue inward<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:4974:21"/> deſired to eate thys paſſeouer wyth you, before that I ſuffer, for I ſay vnto you hence furth I wil not eate of it any more vntyll it be fulfilled in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdome of God and he toke the cup and gaue tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes and ſaied, take this and deuid it amonge you, for I ſaye vnto you, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> will not drinke of the frut of the vine, vntyll the kingdom of god come, and he toke breade and when he hadde giuen thankes he brake it, and gaue it vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, this is my bodye whiche is gi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen for you, thys do in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of me. Like wyſe alſo whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had ſupped he toke the cup ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge, thys cupe is the newe, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, in my bloude whiche is ſhed for you.</p>
            <p>Theſe wordes Sainte Luke <note place="margin">Luk. xxii. Math. xxvi.</note> writeth, the other euangeleſtes wrytte the ſame, but they differ in ſome wordes, as Math ſayed, Drinke all of thys, for thys is my
<pb facs="tcp:4974:21"/> bloude, whiche is the newe teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente that is ſhed for manie, for <note place="margin">Mat. xiiii.</note> the remiſſion of ſynnes, and ſaint Marke ſayth, they al dranke of it meaninge the cup. Saint Paule doth expounde Chriſtes wordes ſayinge thys doo as ofte as you drinke it in remembraunce of me for as often tymes, as you ſhall eate thys breade and drinke thys cup ye ſhall ſhewe furth the Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des death tell he come, but let a man examyne him ſelfe, and ſo let hym eate of the breade and drinke of the cup Saint Iohn doeth not declare the ordinaunce of thys ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.</p>
            <p>But he teacheth, from the .xiii. <note place="margin">Iohn .xiii. xii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> xv. xvii. xviii.</note> Cap. to the .xviii. how Chriſt did vſe his ſupper and what he did at it, he waſhed hys diſciples, fete he preached to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and commaunded them to be in charitie he exhorted them to pacience, he ſtrengthend confirmed and eſtablyſhed their
<pb facs="tcp:4974:22"/> fayth towarde god and praied for them to hys father, but eſpecially he rebuked Iudas the traitor. S. Paule ſayth we beinge many are one breade, and one bodye in <note place="margin">Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſo muche we all are partetakers, of one breade and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Euangeliſtes, reporte that Chriſte dyd finiſhe hys holy ſupper wyth thankes geueyng. The ſome and grounde of the hole matter proponed, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in the ſentences of ſcripture nowe reherſed but becauſe Chriſt ſayth ſerch the ſcripture we ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">Iohn. v.</note> wil are counſaile, of the word of God in other plaſes and debate howe the Lordes ſupper ought to be vſede let vs firſt deuide thes queſtions into foure partes, firſte ſome thinges are common, both to the miniſtre, and receiuour of the Sacrament, moreouer ſome thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges belonge only to the miniſters thyrdly ſome thynges perteyne to the receyuer onely, and finally
<pb facs="tcp:4974:22"/> ſome thinges muſt be obſerued in the ſacramente alone. Firſt let vs expende and conſider what is the dutes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſters and laitie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether at this holly ſupper. Chriſt was the miniſter and the .xii. apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteles, were the receyuers, &amp; laitie <note place="margin">Luke .xxii.</note> for S, Luke ſayth whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the houre was come Chriſt and the .xii. apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtles <note place="margin">i. Co. xiiii.</note> ſate downe to be an exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple to vs to do all thynges in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gacion wyth comlynes and order. For we ſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt, obſerued boeth tyme &amp; place, but yet thoſe ought not to be vnderſtanded that we ſhall leaue the true meanynge, and folowe the bare letter, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme and place was moſt myte, for hym to go about that godly worke, and thankes giuinge, boeth becauſe the eaſter lamb ought to be eaten in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euening, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> night of Chriſts paſſion was at ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d but it is moſt mete, to vs to miniſter that ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, before dinner that the laitie
<pb facs="tcp:4974:23"/> ſhall receyue it ſtandyng and not ſittyng, &amp; alſo that it be broken in two pieces, before the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laitie &amp; not when it is mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred, for the euangeliſtes, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded and decrered nothynge in theſe externe thynge, but an honeſte order, for it is vnpoſſible that we ſhoulde do and obſerue, the ſelfe ſame order of receyueinge the ſacramente that the apoſtles dyd for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no mo then. xii. ſhould receyue it at once And hat of one miniſter it ſhould alſo be recyued in the euening. Moreouer Chriſt did eate the eaſter lambe with his diſciples, and refuſed that bodily meat and drinke ſaying he would eate nomore, of that vntyl it were <note place="margin">Luke. xxii.</note> fulfilled, in the kingdome of God, nor dryncke of the fruite of the vine vntyl the kingedome of God come, that we after hys example ſhoulde neythere ſeke, for a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſupper to fyll the belly nor be
<pb facs="tcp:4974:23"/> addicte &amp; giuen to the obſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the Iuiſhe cerimonies and ſha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dowes of the truth, but that with an vnfayned fayth we ſhoulde w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> thankes giuing receyue the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall fode in the worde and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes of God. Alſo both the mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtres and receiuers ought to come to the Lordes table, in charitie, &amp; proteſte true mutuall loue, one to an other, for Saint Iohn ſayeth Chriſte dyd erneſtly preache, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite <note place="margin">Iohn. xxiii. xiiii. xv. xvi. xvii.</note> to his diſciples and loued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the ende, for we beinge one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregacion are membres of one bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy &amp; bretherne in dede, by Chriſt. For as ſaint Paule ſayth though <note place="margin">i. Cor. x.</note> we be manie, yet are we one bodie when we are partakers, of one breade, finally it is mete that one, tarie for anothere, excepte ſome matter of greate importaunce let vs, and that we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue in praier to thende Iudas alone, departied awaye before the other to his own
<pb facs="tcp:4974:24"/> deſtruction. Saint Paule ſaieth, bretherne whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you come together <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Cor xi,</note> to eate, let one tarie for annother and if any man be hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>grie let hym <note place="margin">Math. xxvi. Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. xiiii.</note> eate at home. Saynte Mathewe and Saint Marke ſaye that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they had ſayed grace, thei we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vp into the hyll of Oliues Nowe let vs learne what is the function and office of the miniſter, and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard of the miſteries of God thys we are taught of Chriſt him ſelfe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> adminiſtracion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to hys diſciples wherein dyuers and ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dri thinges are to be dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly noted &amp; obſerued. Firſt howe he dyd gyue hym ſelfe to al hys diſci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ples and miniſters and in eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to the preachers, beinge an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample in waſhinge of theyr fete, that they ſhould do the ſame and be prompte and redy at all tymes to miniſter, and do ſeruice to eueri man. Moreouer here is to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that Chriſte dyd willingelye
<pb facs="tcp:4974:24"/> and of purpoſe ſhone and abhorre al externe and outwarde pompes and ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne ſightes, that he might printe in oure hertes thynges of greater importaunce, alſo whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had waſhed theire feete. he went agayne to the table and put on <note place="margin">Iohn. xiii.</note> hys accuſtomed rament teaching hys diſciples<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by thys example to go about ſuche thinges as ought to be moſt chifflye regarded, for he then erneſtly preached the Goſpell admoniſhed and rebuked Iudas the teaytoure, and taught his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, to be in charitie pacience, and hope of thynges to come, ſo <note place="margin">Iohn. xvi.</note> plainely &amp; manifeſtlie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſayd you ſpeake not nowe in parables.</p>
            <p>Note alſo that Chriſte gaue <note place="margin">Math. xvi,</note> thankes to God the father, before he gaue the ſacrament to hys diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, exhortynge them to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre <note place="margin">i. Cor xii.</note> and ſhewe furth thereby hys paſſion vntill he come. Finally he callyd vpon hys father wyth a fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent <note place="margin">Iohn. xvii.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:4974:25"/> deſire, and prayed for all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that beliue. Nowe touchinge the <note place="margin">Iohn. xvii.</note> receyuers, of oure Lordes ſupper, they gaue greate attendaunce, to the word &amp; doctrine of Chriſt, and wyth obedience receyued the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the body and bloude, of Chriſte, Saynt Marke ſayeth they al dyd drinke, by hys ſayinge no man is excepted. Finally let vs expende &amp; conſider of what thing <note place="margin">Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. xiiii.</note> the ſacramente is made, vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly it is made of breade wyne, &amp; the worde, for there cannot be the ſacrament of oure Lordes ſupper where any of theſe lacketh, Chriſt verely toke materiall breade and wyne, choſinge them for the vſe of the ſacrament, we reade not that he toke water grapes or any ſuch other thynge, and he ſayede theſe wordes. Thys is my bodie which ſhalbe gyuè for you, and thys cup <note place="margin">Luke. xxii.</note> is the newe teſtamente, in my blould whiche ſhalbe ſhed for you
<pb facs="tcp:4974:25"/> by theſe wordes the bread, &amp; wyne are made the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; holly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of Chriſtes body &amp; bloud, theſe wordes offer to vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> promeſſes of the Ioyful Goſpel, which if we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a true faith, we eate ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tually in ſpirit y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſhe, &amp; bloud of chriſt &amp; therby obtain life eternal.</p>
            <p>The ſacrament is like a writen Teſtament, that promiſeth great gyftes and is ſealed wyth two ſea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les, that ought to be kepte hole &amp; vnbroke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if all theſe thynges afore reherſed, were obſerued and kepte then the Lordes ſupper ſhould be truely vſed, the Maſſe (as they cal it) ſhould perfectlie be holy, for god praiſed therin, would regard it, &amp; we ſhould receyue of it, great frutes &amp; goodnes, for therebye we are enſtructed to beleue in god, &amp; loue oure neighboure excludinge all ſedicion, and diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that peace pacience and concorde, may take place and rule, againſte thys
<pb facs="tcp:4974:26"/> doctrine, nothinge can be proued, and debated by the holy ſcripture for it is grounded on moſte ſure principles, and fundacion, refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe, all thynges to fayeth and <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ti. i. Iohn. i. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i. iii. iiii. v.</note> charitie, by the which two al thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges ought to be tried, paraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture they wyll anſwere, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man can finde faulte wyth oure ſayeinge, but yet it is, expediente to Ioyne other ceremonies wyth the approued vſe in the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracion of thys ſacrament, of our Lordes ſupper as haue been, vſed hitherto, and ſo the hollye thynge ſhalbe worthei the greater praiſe. We aunſwer that it is nomatter thoughe theſe ceremonies, were omited and left whyche were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cogitate, and found out by mans reaſon and a true chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man wil not be offended ther with, as ligh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyng of candeles ſinging, ringing of belles, deckinge of aulters gyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge of Images, veluet and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brodered
<pb facs="tcp:4974:26"/> ornamentes, reliques of ſayntes, Organs prickſonge deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant and ſuch other, which do not edifie the congregacion, that they maye encreaſe in godlines fayeth and charitie, for as Saynt Paul <note place="margin">Act. xv.</note> ſayeth bodely exerciſe, is litel pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, but rather when theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne thinges, are highlie eſtemed and defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded with touth and naile, as we haue ſene, by experience: theſe percepts of god, faith, humi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>litie charite and preachinge of the worde are lytle regarded, when theſe true good things that pleaſe God, &amp; are taught vs of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture do wonderfully worcke in vs godlines, &amp; Iuſtice. If thys mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of ceremoneis had pleaſed God and ben thought profitable to bring men to godlines and ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuouſe liuinge. No doubte but Chriſte woulde haue taugth the, The apoſtles woulde haue obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and kept them, and S Paul
<pb facs="tcp:4974:27"/> woulde haue greately magnified and prayſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and if god would y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his noble workes ſhoulde haue ben had in reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ſetfurth and extolled, wyth ſumptuouſe cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, he woulde haue thaught our fathers of the priuate church to vſe them after a moſt gorgiouſe facion, as they dyd, in Ieruſalem when Solomons temple was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated <note place="margin">i. Regu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. viii.</note> where many fatte Oxen, were ſlayne, and muche monye ſpente alſo when Aaron the high prieſte was conſecrated, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the arke of couenaunte was made if god woulde that we ſhoulde do ſo, thys multitude of ceremonies had ben laufully inſtituted in the primatiue church but chriſt wuld that we ſhoulde be occupied with weightier maters, &amp; leſſe regarde ths externe pompe, then heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye and, celeſtiall for cerimonies, are nothynge but figurs, to ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe and hyde the trueth frome
<pb facs="tcp:4974:27"/> the vnlearned. A man therfore ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſe no better, order in the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracion of oure Lordes ſupper, then that whiche Chriſte him ſelf vſed, but we are not pleaſed wyth Chriſte when we are not pleaſed wyth the order and waye, that he taketh. Naama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> when he diſpiced that playne waye to waſhe hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in Iorda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> remayned alwayes a leper, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he did waſhe him<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe <note place="margin">i. Cor. iii.</note> as the prophete commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded hym he was healped. Verely me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes wyſdome in maters of god, is foliſhnes we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not ſet furth, and miniſter the Lordes ſupper, more purely then when we folowe ther in Chriſte, &amp; his diſciples for that whiche men put to of there owne brayne, without authoritie of ſcri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture is merlie faulce, albe it they aſcribe the ſame to the holly gooſt. What fole hardines is this to ad ioyne their dremes to the ſpirit of God, doeth it of neceſſitie folowe
<pb facs="tcp:4974:28"/> that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> two or three Biſhoppes are aſſembled together, that the holly gooſte doeth decre and make lawes by them? we muſt examine and trye there conſtitucions, and decres, whethere they agree with Chriſtes doctrine, and do extolle teache and eſtabliſhe fayeth, and charitie or no, for in ſo do ynge a man maye eaſlye perceyue that the hollie goſt is not the authour of ſuch dirtie tradicions and low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie lawes, but rather y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie, to thynke that the office of the hollye gooſte is to inſtitute and ordayne ſuche ſuperſticious, and vnprofitable cerimonies.</p>
            <p>They y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> knowe the nature of the holye goſt, by the word of God are aſſured that he commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded not ſuch trifles and ſuperfluouſe thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, to be done, as haue ben con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, and decreed, in mani ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſailes for he doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhadows, of the vnperfite
<pb facs="tcp:4974:28"/> olde law nor laith on chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mens ſhoulders, the yoke, that nother the apoſtles nor fathers of the old teſtamente coulde beare, for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <note place="margin">Math. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> doeth put newe wyne into olde botteles, nothere ſoweth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece of newe cloth into an old gar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t but our aduerſaris moſt blaſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phemouſly affirme that although they conſtitute and ordayne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye ceremonies contrarie to the libertie of the Goſpell and repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunte to Chriſtes ordinaunces yet they are made and ordeined by the holly goſte.</p>
            <p>Now we haue declared the true doctrine of Chriſte, touchinge the adminiſtracion of the ſacramente of oure Lordes ſupper we wyl alſo conſider the popiſhe Maſſe wyth it. Let vs fyrſt ſhewe and declare the abuſe boeth in the functio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and office of the miniſter, and of the receyuer for thys is the chiefe erroure of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> papiſties, not becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:4974:29"/> they do not obſerue tyme &amp; place but foraſmuche they regarde not the libertie of a chriſten man who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſte ſet at libertye wyth ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge of hys owne bloude. And laie ſnares for mens co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſience with preceptes in externe thinges as in orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts oyleing a ſuperſticiouſe auriculare confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and in other like thinges innumerable, for both the miniſters and receiuers of the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thynke it a capital offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce if they omite &amp; leaue any of theſe beggerly tradicions of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> behind and vndon defending them vnder pretence of good order, when ther can be nothyng more confuce and oute of order then to make the Lordes ſupper ſubiecte to mens co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitutions and preceptes in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trene thinges from whiche Chriſt oure maſter made it free.</p>
            <p>They Iudge it a muche more heinouſe offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, to omyte anye of the vayne tradicions of man vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,
<pb facs="tcp:4974:29"/> then if a man ſhould be a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicator, a dicer a dronckeard a blaſphemer of god, or in any other ſuch vices, an abominable ſinner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condeminge of hereſie all ſuch as neglecte theſe ceremonies and vn godly conſtitutcions of theirs, and Chriſtes ordinaunce beynge no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge wourth or wythout there cererimonies inuented of theyr owne brayne, it muſte therefore be a deteſtable abominacion, to trouble chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mens libertie after thys ſorte, for if it myght co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinew ſtyll free, men myghte let orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes paſſe and ſuche other externe thynges, for the holy goſte doeth not teache, them whiche ſet thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges out of order, after thys ſorte. The true honoure and ſeruice, of God is ſubiecte nothere to tyme place nor perſone charitie in ede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiynge thy neyghboure, in theſe thynges, oughte to rule all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregacions. For al chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacions
<pb facs="tcp:4974:30"/> vſe not one kynde, and or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der in theyre cerimonies. Them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peroure Charles firſte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name dyd laboure to bryng al churches to agree in one kynde and order of ceremonies but he coulde neuer bring it to paſſe, for it was againſt god, and therefore it coulde neuer be brought to effect. If we ſhould be compelled to obſerue and kepe ſuche preceptes of men being pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fitable nother to fayth nor chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may Iudge that we haue not yet eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the eaſter lambe, that is to ſaye. That greater burdens, are leyde on oure neckes, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euer was on the Iues which thing is abominacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before God, and that they haue done ſo to vs, the deuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſitie of ornamentes, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther foliſhe cerremonies, whiche they haue borowed of the Iues, do manifeſtly declare and teſtifie as it ſhall appeare hereafter. Alſo they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temne theyre neighbours
<pb facs="tcp:4974:30"/> which beliue in Chriſt, and deſire to be incorporate, to him by chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate, curſe, and ſuſpen de them for not obſeruyng ſome of theire vaine ceremonies wherein they breake charitie whiche ought chifely to remayne amonge them that, are pertakers of the Lordes ſupper. There is no true chriſten churche, where cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie is not, al that churche there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wyth the Maſſe, is obomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble before god.</p>
            <p>The praires of that congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, are not harde of God whiche fereth not to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <note place="margin">Eſai. i.</note> Chriſtes bodie &amp; bloud, wyth her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ful of enuye malice &amp; hatered, and with ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des ful of bloud final<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly if any thyng be abominable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore god it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe, for it oppreſſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> liberte, it hath brough in a greate multitude of Iueſhe <note place="margin">Gala. iiii. v.</note> cereimonies, and hath no regarde to chriſten charitie. ſ Paule ſpeake<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:4974:31"/> of the conſciens exhorteth vs to perſiſte, in libertie, and ſuffer not oure ſelues to be leade vnder the yoke of bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dage. Alſo he teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs, that oure workes are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable without charitie. Now let vs declare and ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the abuſes of the miniſters we frely knoledg and confeſſe that al thoughe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye miniſters of the ſacramente be vnmete and reprouide of god, throughe theyr abominable and vicious liuing, yet the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts remayne ſacramentes, throughe the miniſtracion of the worde, but thys we affirme, that the vertue and efficacie of the ſacramentes is not like, neither y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy goſt work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth like effect whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> receiueth the ſacramentes of an vngodlye, and impudente ſinner, and when he receyueth them of agodlye, and true chriſten man for albeit the ſacramente is preſent, yet ther is in it neither grace nor vertue
<pb facs="tcp:4974:31"/> for both y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſinner &amp; he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tth are equallie puniſhed as both the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eres, and ſellers of Doues were driuen out of the temple: ſo both the miniſter of the ſacrament, and the receyuer ſhalbe gyltie of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes <note place="margin">Luke. xviiii.</note> bodye and bloude. Theſe miniſter is giltye becauſe he doth miniſter vnwortheylye for truly <note place="margin">i. Co. ii.</note> hys ſeruice is abominable before god for if ther were, no worſe thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges then the lyuynge of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters to make the Maſſe and an bominacion before God, yet theire impuritie of lyfe, is inoughe to make it vnpure and filthy before the face of God. By what place of ſcripture can they proue, that the Maſſe is holy, accepted of god, and a profitable worke for the quicke and deade of what miniſtrie ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it be ſaied? In dede by non for how can the deade helpe the dead, eithere a ſynner make a ſynner
<pb facs="tcp:4974:32"/> rightouſe, euery man knowynge that ſynne pleaſeth not god, maye perceyue what theye can do with God, for what ſo euer is not of fayeth is ſinne. Their Maſſe ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om. xiiii.</note> is ſynne and abominable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God.</p>
            <p>Nowe let vs conſider what fu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and office Chriſte throughe hys owne exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to the miniſtres &amp; ſtewardes of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he waſhed his diſciples fete, it was done to teach the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of goddes worde that they ſhoulde not exaulte them ſelues as Lordes and maiſters ouer the laytye, for Saynte Peter ſayeth, thelders, ought to be an example and mirrour to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flocke of Chriſt for pride is a greate abominacion before God Chriſte iruly can not be pleaſed wyth ſeruauntes that are puffed vppe wyth pryde. But where is ther any humilitie amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges them? none at all. I wyll not
<pb facs="tcp:4974:32"/> ſpeake of there ſhaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> crownes, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſiluer ſtaues, byſhoppes rin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, or other ſuch coſtlye, and riche robes, and ornamentes, In deede thei are much more precious, then Chriſtes poure ſimple garmentes but truely: the remembraunce of Chriſtes paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, cannot be ſhewed furth after the ryght waye in ſuch more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> princelie aparell. For no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther goulde nor ſiluer was ſene at Chriſtes death albeit they, by this riche rayment haue inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted and deuiſed, a gliſteringe pretence, of miſticall vnderſtanding, Saynt. <note place="margin">i. Pe. ii.</note> Peter coulde not, ſuffre exceſſe of apparrile in gentylwomen, much leſſe in the adminiſtracion of our Lorddes Supper, and in them that ſhould be an example to al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>there in Godly conuerſacion and lyuynge, theire prydde can not be hyd, for they beleue, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure to perſwadde other that by the Byſhoppes anoynetynge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a
<pb facs="tcp:4974:33"/> marke is printed in their ſoules, whereby they are made of greater authoritie, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> angels or ſ. Marye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> virgin. yea, and this marke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſay they, can by no meanes be put awaie They extole therfore, them ſilues, aboue al men and ſet them ſelues at libertye, frome all bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denes, and bondage, that other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are charged wyth all their wyl is to be Lordes ouer all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; all ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice due to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Thei magnifi &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tolle, ther prayers in there holly Maſſe and ſet the popes name be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the, kynges in theyr canon, if a man yea a good, and godly ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> touche the Chalice nor the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by chaunce, it is a Capitall offence, they iudge it an heinouſe abominacion, to miniſtre, the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament to the laitie vnder boeth kindes. And why becauſe they are not anointede, and made popiſhe prieſtes. Their prid alſo is opened and ſhewed furth nothynge more
<pb facs="tcp:4974:33"/> then in their offring and ſacrifice for they are fully perſwaded that they offre to god, his ſonne Ieſus Chriſte, for remiſſion of ſynnes, boeth for quicke and deade.</p>
            <p>This preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptuouſe arogancie, muſt nedes be an abomination be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore god, a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cannot find in theſe proud papiſtes, neither liberalitie in doinge of good dedes, or ſeruice to other where vnto they are chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffelie choſine. But it is theire pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie to ſerue dame Aueris, and their owne bealis. If rewarde be promiſed, they are redye to ſynge Maſſe, but if no reward come the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyll they nother ſynge nor ſaye. For no peny, no pater noſter. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedlye <note place="margin">Eph. vi.</note> euerie couetouſe man is an Idolater. For where coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſenes reigneth, as Saynte Paule ſayeth, there is Idolatrie, which is abominacion before god Theſe couetuouſe popiſhe prieſts are therefore, abominable before
<pb facs="tcp:4974:34"/> god. And another ſorte of theſe pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piſtes wyll ſynge Maſſe, not for monie, but for feare of loſing their fate promocions But what great ſynne is thys to do theſe thynges againſt their conſcience? For they do it fearinge leaſte other wyſe they ſhoulde wante a liuing. Oh what miſtruſt haue they in God who fedeth and clotheth birdes, and other liuinge creatures, and thus haue they made a banket of the moſte holly ſupper of our lord, for fylthy lucre and gaynes. If a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſhoulde deſier one of the lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which is a good and godly ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to receiue the ſacrament, and he ſhould haue for his laboure a cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of grotes or a teſtarne, he wold not onely refuſe it, but greuouſly taking y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mater, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould haue ſuche an opinion in hym.</p>
            <p>Notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinge theſe Maſſe mongers thynke it greate honeſtie to receyue money for their Maſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge,
<pb facs="tcp:4974:34"/> when it is to their greate ſhame and rebuke. Thys ſaing of Saint Paule, he that ſerueth the aulter muſte lyue alſo therof: doth not make for them for S. Paulle <note place="margin">i. Cor. ix.</note> doth teach nothynge elſes by thys ſainge, but that the preachers of the Goſpel may without groudge of conſcience prouide of the godes of the churche, for ſuche thynges as they lacke. And this argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, is taken of the preiſtes of tholde lawe. That as they had there li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge, for offringe of ſacrifices, ſo the miniſtres, of the goſpel ſhould haue their liuinge, for preaching of the ſame. For Saynt Paul did no more meane by thys texte, that prieſtes ſhoulde ſynge Maſſe for the quicke and deade then he pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, to teache men, howe to war Their ente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, is not to ſerue Chriſt oure true aulter, but the god ther <note place="margin">Heb. iii.</note> owne bealies wo be to them, that mayntayne, thys patched popiſhe
<pb facs="tcp:4974:35"/> Maſſe, either with rewardes cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle or any other waye, for in ſo doinge they geue no leſſe occaſion to theſe papiſtes to commite moſte heinouſe offences then the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies &amp; rulars of the people, did to Iudas the traytoure. Here we o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myte and paſſeouer theyr filthye, whoredome, continual hate mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſe, enuie vnfruitful Idelnes, and ſuche othere abominacions whiche make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reprouable, both before god and man, and through thys theyr vngodlye conuerſacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, all men for the moſt parte, are dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen from the true ſeruice of God a man therfore cannot think how much god aborreth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. If theſe proude impudent pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piſtes, had neuer ſo little remorſſe of conſcience, they would abhorre, and be aſhamed of them ſelues. Fayne theſe Maſſe mongers the popes creatures, to be godlie libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and that they are not proude
<pb facs="tcp:4974:35"/> in their ornamentes and ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, but walke in chriſten libertie notwythſtandinge the contrarie is playnly ſeene in them, yet they woulde men, ſhoulde haue ſuche oppinion in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And let vs come to ther function and office wherin they can do nothing wel and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, nether wyth good wyll, nor in knowledge. Our lordes Supper ought neuer to be miniſtred with out the remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Chriſtes death, nor wythout a ſermon, or exhortacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and that in a la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>guage that the congregacion maye per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fictly vnderſtande, to theyr edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacion, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cor. xiiii.</note> as Chriſte alſo taught, his diſciples. In the maſſe is nothing but mockes, and they make Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie of the Goſpel and Epiſtiles which the holy goſte gaue vs for our conſolacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> correction and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortacion But theſe popiſh, prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes haue made of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an externe pompe, extollynge them ſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue
<pb facs="tcp:4974:36"/> the Iues and Gentiles, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there gliſtringe ſhewes, of vaine ceremonies the Ieues and Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles therfore laught the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſcorne vſinge them as foles and mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. The Euangeleſtes require an other kynde of working, and ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>erciſe, then ſenſinge waſtinge of candles, ſinging of prickſong and kiſſinge of golden bokes. It were more mete to preache the grace of our lord Ieſus Chriſt, but Chriſt is not ſpoken of at al, amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and the lyght y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhoulde be ſet vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the candelſticke, is hide vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> buſhell. Nowe where the worde of God, is kepte vnder and hyd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye ther is nothynge, but dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and errour we haue therefore plainly declared and proued that thys hinderaunce of Gods worde is an heinouſe abominacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſyght of God. And thys is out of queſtion that euerie Maſſe wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in the word of god is not preached
<pb facs="tcp:4974:36"/> and that in a language that the congregacion maye vnderſtande it, is a moſte pyuyſhe Idolatrye. But as they folowe not Chriſt in there ſermons and preachinge, ſo do thei not obſerue his order &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner, of thankes giueinge, and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer. For they haue ſuche a rable of vaine ceremonies, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuoute pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, can haue no place they haue alſo many collectes, that true chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought not to ſaye. Many reade, that which they vnderſtand not. When they Maſſe for monye &amp; other cauſes afore reherſed, how can it be poſſible, that they being whore mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers and al togither car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally mynded, ſhoulde praye and gyue thankes wyth a deuoute and pure conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Thoughe they alſo ſeme to them ſelues, to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoute <note place="margin">Math. vi.</note> men yet in prayinge, they make much lip laboure and theyr <note place="margin">Mal. ii.</note> hertes are far of. Thei are therfor abominable before god. For as he
<pb facs="tcp:4974:37"/> ſayeth, by Malachias, there bleſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge ſhalbe accurſed. When they come to the diſtrubucion of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, they breake it, in there pieces one piece for the quicke, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother for them that are in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and the thyrde for the deade beinge in purgatorie, and at laſte eate all them ſelues but it were more mete to fede others, and be without the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues. They ordeine a feaſt, and cal no geſtes to it, nor wyll eate of one lofe, and one cupe amonge them ſelues: but euerye man wyll haue hys owne aultare his owne lof and cup. Wherin do theſe thynges agre with our Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ſupper.</p>
            <p>Neither Iwe nor gentile, can mocke and delude Chriſtes ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, more then theſe vngodly wretches, it is maruaile that the eareth openeth not to ſwalowe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quicke in to hell. Nowe touch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ynge the laytye it were agaynſte
<pb facs="tcp:4974:37"/> reaſone, to rebuke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but rather to be ſorye, and beare wyth theire weaknes, and ignoraunce. Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer commeth to our Lordes ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble, oughte to heare the worde of God, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles dyd. But howe ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they here, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preacheth They ought to make an anſwere, and ſaye Amen to their prayer. But thei nother know nor vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtande, what they ſaye and ſo they ertol and magnifie noughtie and vaine trifeles for frutfull and god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>li matters, and for the liuely word of God they beleue in fonde foliſh fables. It is neceſſarie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we praye to God that hys people maye be deliuered, from the hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger of gods worde, that they may knowe how miſerabli, they haue ben deceiued by theſe faulſe preachers. What ſhal the vnlearned people do, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lyes and erroures ſo muche pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, and thei being captiues, and priſoners vnder Antichriſt, godes
<pb facs="tcp:4974:38"/> enemie. They receiue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrament but once in the yere, and in one kind contrary to Chriſtes, ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce It muſte therfore be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull, and abominable before God when hys churche is ſpoyled and diſtroyed after ſuche ſorte. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally there are ſome erroures and abominacions founde in the very ſacramente. For the materiall ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtaunce of it ought to be bread and wyne, as it is in dede, as S. Paul <note place="margin">i. Cor. xi.</note> ſo calleth it both before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on &amp; after. But the papiſtes, teach y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, not her bread nor wyne remayne after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecracion but accidentes only y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is, collour ſauour taſte rud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines and ſuch other. And w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch manifeſt lies they blind mens eies to beleue that, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> thing is in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament whiche is not there, and that, that is not in the ſacrament which is ther in dede.</p>
            <p>Allexander firſt pope of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name decred and ordiened. That water
<pb facs="tcp:4974:38"/> ſhoulde be menglide, wyth wyne, whyche thynge is repungnaunte to Chriſtes ordinaunce. For he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded no ſuche thynge to be done. If we wyll expend, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, the wordes of Chriſte oure Maſter, touching this ſacrament we maye eaſly perceiue what Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than goeth aboute. The papiſtes mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble in latine, &amp; the belles make ſuch ringinge that the heares, can not vnderſtand what is ſayde, or ſong. They haue put to alſo, in the conſecracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wordes that are not in the Goſpel as Enim trulie, &amp; Eleuatis oculis in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lifting vp his eies to hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And Eterni Of the euerlaſting. Alſo Miſteriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Fidei. The miſterie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fayeth. But theſe are maters of ſmal weight, thei leaue vnſaid wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des of grater importau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which is Quod pro nobi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> trad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tur aut frangitur. That ſhalbe deliuered or broken for you. And me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s eares are ſtopped w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> plaing one the organs, &amp; deſcante ſonges.
<pb facs="tcp:4974:39"/> When theſe wordes are ſpoken leaſte, they ſhoulde doubte in any thynge that is ſaide. If the people remembre chriſtes paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time the prieſtes are not thankes wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie, for they ſhoulde boeth reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre, the wordes of the paſſion, and alſo giue thankes to God for the ſame, but they ſhall not do ſo, if the prieſtes can let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. It is ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, manyfeſt that the papiſtes fo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowe not Chriſtes example in the ſupper at theyr popiſhe Maſſe yet they ſaye there Maſſe is holie whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there is nothinge more vnhollye. They bragge that ſaynte Iames dyd vſe thys Maſſe at Ieruſalem Saynte Marke at Alexandria, and Saynte Peter at Antioche: but they haue no hiſtorie touche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge thys matter worthy credite. Though they vſed our lordes ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per, as Chriſte oure mayſter dyd and as S Paule alſo at Corinth: yet they dyd not vſe it as the py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe
<pb facs="tcp:4974:39"/> papiſtes do now the Maſſe. That Ignatius, Policarpe &amp; Ire<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neus make mencion of, is not like this popiſhe maſſe. Thei confeſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Baſilius Magnus Ihero<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e &amp; Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bros vſede another order, in the adminiſtracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our Lordes ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, then is nowe vſed and that diuerſe haue vſed, diuerſe facio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s therin, by ther own wordes. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore it is manifeſte, that this kind of maſſinge is not the ordinaunce of Chriſte, but inuented by mans wyt, and policie without y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of God. And nowe I wyll declare by the teſtimonie of aunciente hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories what popes, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they patchilde together this beggerlye Maſſe of theires.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>☞ Halowing of aultares and temples.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ Felix, friſt pope, of that name, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded temples and aultars to be hallowed in the yere of oure Lorde God. cclxix.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>☞ Aulters</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>us, firſte of that name,
<pb facs="tcp:4974:40"/> ordeined aulters and Sayntes, in the yere of oure Lorde. Cxxiiii.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>☞ Aultar clothes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ Boniface commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded aul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tares to be couered w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fyne linnen cloth, in the yere of our Lord. cccx</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chalices.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ Vrban and Seuerine or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined challices of goulde and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, in the yere of our Lorde. ccxv.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>☞ Albes and corporaſſes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ Silueſter dyd ordayne, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes and corporaſſes in the yere of our Lord. cccxiii.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>☞ Candeles and ornamentes,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ Gregory dyd ordayne, lyght at maſſe, &amp; certaine Ornamentes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yere of our Lord. ccccclxxxxii.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>☞ Proceſſion</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ Agabetus dyd ordayne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion on Sondayes, aboute the churche in the yere of oure Lorde. cccccxxxii.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>☞ Holly water.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ Alexander did ordeine wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be mingled wyth wyne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuened breade and holly water in
<pb facs="tcp:4974:40"/> the yere of our Lord. cxii.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>☞ Confiteor and the office</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ Pontianus ordeined Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teor before maſſe in the yere of our Lord. ccxxv. And Seleſtinus y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yere of our lord. ccccxxiiii</p>
            <p>
               <hi>☞ Kyrie eleiſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Gregori dyd ordayne, Kyrie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſon at Maſſe in the yere of oure Lorde. ccccclxxxxii.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Gloria in excelſis</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Teleſphorus, made Gloria in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excelſis, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yere of our lord. cxxix</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Collectes and grayle</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Gelaſius made the Collectes Preface, and graile, in the yere of our Lord. CCCC. lxxxx.</p>
            <p>Anaſtaſius ordeined that we ſhoulde ſtande, when the Goſpell is read in the yere of oure Lorde. CCCCix.</p>
            <p>Martine made the Crede in the yere of oure Lord cccxxxiiii.</p>
            <p>¶ The canon is patched toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of many, and therefore one ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is repugnau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wyth an other
<pb facs="tcp:4974:41"/> many ſuperſtouſe wordes are in it they call vpon certayne peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>are Sayntes in it.</p>
            <p>And offer for ſoules, in purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie thei bleſſe &amp; croſſe as if greate vertue and powere were therin, and reade nothinge ſo reuerently as this theyr clouted canon.</p>
            <p>Gregory made the Offertorye &amp; Damaſus gloria patri. They ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not therfore ſaye, that they mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, the ſacramentes of oure Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ſupper as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles dyd whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their doctrine is repugnau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trarie, one to a nother. Thys is ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fficiente to proue that the Maſſe ſhould be abhorred becauſe it doth laye for mens conſience, ſnares of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s tradicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Thei wil haue the prieſtes to be as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prieſtes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde lawe &amp; bring, ſhadows in tyme of light, ſtretching out the armes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidinge the hoſtes, and ſuch other Ieuiſh cuſtomes It was therfore, the dyueles deuiſe to brynge in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:4974:41"/> the churche, ſuche lewde lawes for the true liuing worde of God. If circumciſion, hurteth as S. Paule, witneſſeth, who can denye that the prieſthod of Aro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, varietie of ornamentes, and anoyntynge, do nothinge auaile and profite in thys tyme of the newe law. Much leſſe profite is therfore receyued of mans inuentions and vayne drea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes, that kepe men occupied from the exerciſe of true godlines, &amp; hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie of minde. And excite mens hertes wyth ſingynge and organ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playng to acertayne carnall delite and pleaſure, rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true glory of god as dyd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> groue which was by the temple of Ieruſalem albeit therefore theſe cerimonies are gliſterynge in me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s eis yet they are vile, and of no reputacion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt, who requireth not the viſour and ſhadow of a thyng, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> veri thing it ſelfe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe therfore which was ordiened and conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:4974:42"/> of Antichriſt, and maintayned of his moſt beſt aſſured adherentes is an abominacion before God, throughe this externe pompe and ſuche other thinges, afore reherſed Finally they fere not to ſaye, that Chriſtes bodie is offered in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe I wyll not contende, and ſtryue wyth them if they take, this word offer to ſignifie remembre, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to the ſence and meanynge of Chriſtes wordes, albeit the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters alone pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and ſpeake theſe wordes. Yet ſuch tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and remembraunce belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not only to them alone, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to the whole congregacion. We deny not that the Doctoures cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Maſſe an offeringe, whiche is the remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of an offering once made as Sainte Auguſtine doeth playnely, declare ſayeinge in thys offering is tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes giuing and remembraunce of Chriſtes bodie, and bloude which he offered
<pb facs="tcp:4974:42"/> and ſhede for vs But the papiſtes are not pleaſed wyth this offering for they wil haue, a greater offring which is an offering repreſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tatiue when Chriſte dyed once for euer, and ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> die nomore. They ſaye that theſe wordes (do thys in my reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce) ſignifie the conſecracion, offering and reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, but this is a faulſely deuiſed and forgide interpretation. For Chriſte at hys holly and Sacrete ſupper, Tooke breade and gaue thankes, brake it and gaue it to his diſciples.</p>
            <p>Commaundynge them to eate, and in like wyſe the wyne. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he preached to them hys death and paſſion that they ſhoulde do after hys example, wyth a ſincere &amp; true fayth, and there is not one Iotte, that can proue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> adminiſtracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this moſt bleſſed ſacramente to be an offering, repreſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tatiue of Chriſt his owne offering, and althoughe Chriſt woulde haue had, his bodie
<pb facs="tcp:4974:43"/> preſent, bodily in this breade, yet in no wiſe his wordes ſignifie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he offered him ſelfe in thys holie ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for he woulde haue gyuen hys bodie to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reallie, &amp; not in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramente, It is not inoughe, for theſe piuiſhe papiſtes to offer chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes bodie to God except they offer it alſo for remiſſion of ſynne, for health of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodie and for hope of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal life. For other wiſe it ſhuld not be ſo highly eſtemed. If they continewe ſtill in theſe errours, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the plaine trueth, they will <note place="margin">The belefe of a true chriſtian. Ro. iiii.</note> deny Chriſt. For he that knoweth Chriſte, is certainely aſſured that he is god, and man the ſauiour of the worlde, that in hym, as in the true ſede of Dauid, al nacions are bleſſed and that no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can come to the father but by him. For the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">Ga. iii. Iohn. xi.</note> doth ſo loue him, that for hys ſake, his angre toward vs is paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied for he is our rightuouſnes, ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lines and redempcion that noma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <note place="margin">Cor. i.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:4974:43"/> is ſaued, but bi his name only that he alone fulfilled, the worke of our <note place="margin">Act. iiii.</note> redempcion with out any helper. And finally, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he did ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfie <note place="margin">Eſae. lxiii.</note> for our ſinnes on the croſſe if we beliue truely on him. This is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. x.</note> ground, of our chriſten faith, wher on chriſtes church is builded. And <note place="margin">Math. xvi.</note> he that denieth Chriſte to be hys perfecte, and ſufficient redemer by once ſufferinge death on the croſſe maketh him an vnſufficient prieſt and vnable, redemer. And therfore they deny Chriſt in that they deni his ful power and vertue in our re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Theſe Maſkinge Maſſe prieſtes, in their often offeringe of Chriſte denye that we are Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by fayth only aſcribinge part of oure iuſtificacion to good workes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> playne ſcriptures of <note place="margin">Eph, ii.</note> God for we are ſaued by grace, and not of workes And they mag<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifie and extolle the Maſſe aboue all other good workes, makeinge
<pb facs="tcp:4974:44"/> them ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lues fellowe prieſtes, wyth Chriſt wherin they ſhew, of what generacion, they be euen as they ſprynge of Lucifer, the father of pride, nowe let vs expende and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, whether Chriſte commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his diſciples, to make an offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe of the ſacrament, of his holy ſupper or whether he offered, hym ſelfe therein or no. Vndoubtedly, Chriſtes wordes, diligently obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and noted we maye perceyue eaſlye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſt offred no ſacrifice, therein. To take and breake bread doth not ſignifye to offre. To geue thankes is not to do ſacrifice, for elles he hadde done ſacrifice in fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge, fyue thouſand w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the fewe barlye loues, to gyue his diſciples to eate. And to ſay do this in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>braunce of me, in ſhewynge furth the Lordes death, vntyll he come, is not an offering. To belyue that Chriſt was giuen vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he gaue his bodie to death for vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhed his
<pb facs="tcp:4974:44"/> bloud, not at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſupper, but on the croſſe to redeme vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſyn, is not an offering Finally to proue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beleue on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded in the teſtament, doth not ſignifie to offre. How wyl you nowe proue your, offerynge in the Maſſe. We come to the Lordes table we take and eate, truſteinge in Chriſtes promeſſes, howe do we the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, gyue to him againe. If a king ſhoulde gyue a ringe to a pore ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for a gage, not that he ſhoulde be heire of hys landes and goods, but that it ſhould helpe hym, and that he thereby ſhoulde remember his liberalitye, &amp; mercye, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people myght co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mende, and prayſe hym for that facte, the pore man recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth it to giue it agayne, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king thynkinge to do hym a great plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to make hym riche wyth hys own gift, wer not this a mad ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? So may al ſuch be Iudged, as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fere to Chriſt agayne, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whych he
<pb facs="tcp:4974:45"/> gaue vs for our owne vſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, and that thereby we ſhoulde kepe in remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce his loue, and mercye towarde vs. Chriſt did not lifte vp the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ouer his head as theſe proude papiſtes do. They obiecte and ſaye that God ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> giue ſome thynges, and receyue them agayne, as the ſacrifices of tholde lawe. Thoughe they were the gif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes <note place="margin">Pſal. x,</note> of God, Yet they were gyuen to hym agayne, and thoughe a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite herte is the gyfte of god, yet it is a ſacrifice to God. If we were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded, to offer ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice as they were, then theire ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection ſhoulde be of ſome ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth and efficacie. But wee haue no ſuche commaundemente neyther the ſcriptures make mencion of theſe popiſhe ſacrifices. For Chriſt is of greater power and reputacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then that theſe proude popiſh pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, other can or oughte to offer hym to hys father. Chriſte ſitteth
<pb facs="tcp:4974:45"/> on the fathers ryght hande, and once ſatiſfied for the ſynnes of the <note place="margin">Atc. vii.</note> true Chriſten church, with a moſt ſufficient and perfecte ſacrifice.</p>
            <p>Dare we then moſte miſerable wretches enterpriſe, to do thys thynge agayne. He that doth offre vp ſacrifice is better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. They therefore are better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſte their ſacrifice, he offred vs a ſacrifice to God, and do we goo about to offer hym? He that offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vp ſacrifice, ought to be as pure as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrifice. Oh howe pure they make Chriſt nowe. He as a te<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtament maker, gaue his diſciples the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in his ſupper, none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as a writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, wherin by fayth in Chriſt, we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue Chriſtes bodie &amp; bloude, the vertue and frutes of the ſame. If wee gyue hym hys teſtamente a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne as if he required it of vs, ſhould not we haue the teſtament maker in a contempt? And ſhould <note place="margin">Aba. xi.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:4974:46"/> not the promiſe in the teſtamente, be of effecte? Who ahboreth not thys kynde of blaſphemie, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we conſider the hyghnes of Chriſtes prieſthod and what this worde ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice contayneth in it, we maye eaſlye perceyue what Iniury we do to thynke that we offer Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes bodye as the papiſtes do S. Paule declareth vnto vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> priſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hod of chriſt ſaiing it is mete y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we <note place="margin">Hebru. vii</note> haue ſuche a godly and vndefiled byſhop, made higher then heaues whych nedeth not, to offre dayly. Firſt for hys owne ſinnes, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the ſynnes of the people as the byſhop of the olde lawe for Chriſt dyd thys once in offeringe vp hys owne bodye, and in an other place he ſayth Chriſte beinge the hyghe prieſt, of the good thinges to come came by a greater, and more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte Tabernacle, whiche was not made wyth handes that is to ſaye was not of thys kynde of bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.
<pb facs="tcp:4974:46"/> Neither came he by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloud of gotes and calues but by hys owne bloude, he entred once into thys holly place, and founde eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall redempcion, for we are made hollie, bi godes fre mercie, through the offering of chriſtes bodie done once for all. For Chriſte verely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge one ſacrifice, offred vp for our ſinnes, ſitteth on his fathers right hand, lokeing for the thing that re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mayneh vntil his enemiſe be made his foteſtole, for wyth one offring he made perfecte, thoſe that are ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified. Saynt Paule teacheth vs by Melchiſedech. That Chriſt is king of peace &amp; rightuouſnes. By theſe places of ſcripture it is Manifeſt that Chriſt, ought to be offred no more. For Chriſtes death is ſo per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fect a ſacrifice, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one offering we are made cleane from ſinne for euer. And touchinge his bodie he is no more in thys worlde. There is to be noted that Saynt Paule
<pb facs="tcp:4974:47"/> ſayeth that Chriſte is once offered The papiſtes, ſaye often. He ſaieth all thinges are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſummate &amp;, made perfecte by one ſacrifice. The papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes wil haue moneie maſſes. Note alſo that Chriſte offered hym ſelfe and ſo dyd not the churche byſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opes nor prieſtes, and thys worde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſummate or made perfecte doeth blanke them, that they haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to anſwere, for the holy goſt confuteth theyr ſophiſtrie and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilacions, wyth ſo manifeſte and playne argumentes as can not be denied.</p>
            <p>Note alſo thys worde euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinge. Chriſte is an euerlaſtynge prieſte, for he made ſatiſfaction, for all the ſynne of the whole worlde, and this ſacrifice hath a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all efficacitie, and vertue in all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that beleue in it, and ſhew it forth wyth tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes giuinge for the ſame It is truely a great vntha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kfulnes to ſay it is neceſſarie to offer chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:4974:47"/> againe, an other waye for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſinnes of the worlde. They ſeke manye e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations to defende their often off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. One is thys they ſay Chriſt offreth hym ſelfe Sacramentally, &amp; thei are but miniſtres. But thei declare not this worde ſacrament what thyng it is, leſte they ſhould vtter the truth. The ſacrament is no nother thynge then a token, for vs to remembre, that Chriſt being an only ſacrifice, toke awaye oure ſynnes once on the croſſe. If they woulde declare it after thys ſorte, we ſhoulde ſone agre. But when no man doeth reſiſte them herein they maye doo wyth there Maſſe what ſo euer pleaſeth them. They rule fortune at theyr owne plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Victorie in battaile is optai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned bi their Maſſe, ſatiſfaction for ſinne, &amp; what thinge is it that the Maſſe cannot do. And they make theyr boſtes, that they deſerue by this holi worke what thing ſo euer
<pb facs="tcp:4974:48"/> is needful. But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are put to there anſwer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei fly to this euacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> afore reherſſed Chriſte offe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth hym ſelfe therin, &amp; we are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge elles but miniſters theyr cannon which they magnifie and extoll aboue the goſpell, doeth ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifeſtlie ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and detecte theire vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>godlines, and blaſphemi, for before they come to the conſecracion thei ſaye I offre preſente and gyue to God an holye and vndefiled ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, for the peace of the whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregacion of holly churche, when as it is nothynge but breade and wyne. And it is named the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment And albeit they beliue, that it is not then oure Lordes bodye, yet they offer it fore all the world. This muſt nedes be plaine Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie to gyue to breade and wyne, the honour and glorie of Chriſte who gaue hymſelfe for the church to reconſile and make hys father, atone wyth vs. Howe can Chriſte offer
<pb facs="tcp:4974:48"/> offre himſelfe in the ſacrament be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore he is ther? I thinke men maye nowe eaſlye perceyue howe muche their lies, and anſwere differ fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e their dedes and maſſes. What an heinouſe offence is thys to offre, a peice of breade, &amp; a litle wine, for the onely Sacrifice of Chriſte the highe prieſte. And ſhal y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread and wyne be of lyke efficacitye, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to redeme ſynne with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloud of Ieſus Chriſte? But they are muche more blaſphemouſe after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conſecracion ſayng, that the bread and wyne are tourned into the na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turall bodye, and bloude of Chriſt for they ſaye, we offre to thy holly maieſtye, an holly offeringe, holy breade of lyfe euerlaſting, and cup of euerlaſtynge health, whiche we praye the vochſafe to regarde and loke vpon, wyth thy moſte merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful eies, and cherful countenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and let them be as acceptable to the as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reward of rightuouſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:4974:49"/> &amp; ſacrifice of our father Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an hollye &amp; cleane ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crifice that thei may be brought to thin altar by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> handes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> angel. Theſe are the wordes of the ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>non If they ſpeake of Chriſte, as they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d it, how ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their Imaginacion take place, where they ſaye, that Chriſte offred hym ſelfe in the ſacramente. For they praie for Chriſte, and deſire of god that he maye be in ſuche fauoure wyth God as Abel and Abraham and that the Angell maye brynge hym to the aultar of god. For they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not take bread of eternal life to ſignifie the people, although chriſt were in the breade bodelye, yet he ſhoulde not be offered to God for that were great, derogacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to the honour of hys prieſthod. Great in conuenience doeth folowe to ſaye that the Maſſe is a ſacrifice for ſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes. For ſaynt Paule ſayeth, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuenes of ſynnes is not without
<pb facs="tcp:4974:49"/> ſheddinge of bloude. Howe is Chriſt then offered in the Maſſe when there is no offeringe wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bloude, for if there be any ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, that ſuffereth not and is without bloude. Saynt Paules Argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes are foliſhe, and of no ſtrength or vertue, ſaying. Chriſt offreth hymſelfe no more or elles he muſte neceſſarily dye once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, and muſt haue died often<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tymes ſens the begininge of the worlde. But vndoubtly, S Paul doeth knowe the true ſence and meaneinge of holly ſcripture bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any of al the papiſtes. For a ſacrifice for ſinne is neuer offred without bloud. This ſaying ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore, that ſome thing was offered in the olde lawe, as breade wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bloude, maketh nothinge for there purpoſe. For when the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes of lyuinge creatures are ſlayne, and ſacrifice is offered for ſinnes, bloude muſt be ſhed. Thei
<pb facs="tcp:4974:50"/> cannot therefore proue, by ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that Chriſtes bloude is offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the Maſſe, otherwyſe then in remembraunce, and thankes giuing. And thys is done both of the miniſters and receiuours. For as prayer, ſo thankes giuing alſo belongeth, to al men. He that geueth thankes, ſayeth not I o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffer any thing more than a than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full herte and prayſe to God. If the people were taught thys do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. They woulde not beſtowe ſomuch monie on maſſes and vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dacions of chauntries, and fraternities as they haue done, throughe perſuacion, that remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſynnes, is obtayned in the Maſſe, not by grace promiſed to them that beleue, but by offering of Chriſte the ſonne of God and by prayeinge for hym. Phie, I am aſhamed, to reherſſe thys abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable balaſphemie of theirs in ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters of God. The papiſtes in as
<pb facs="tcp:4974:50"/> muche as in them lyeth, kill and crucifie Chriſte agayne in there ſacrifice of the Maſſe, doinge no other wyſe then if Chriſte as yet were not aſcended into heauen, to hys father he that doeth thys, maketh Chriſte ſubiecte to death and crucifieth hym agayne. For Chriſte entred not nor entreth in to the hollye place of heauen, but by his bloud. Let vs labour, that Chriſt maye dwell in oure hertes They obeicte, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> if it be derogaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Chriſtes honour, and digni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie, and that the merite of hys pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſion be not perfecte becauſe we o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffer Chriſte agayne: fayeth, Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme and kepinge of godes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes maye diminiſhe the dignitie of Chriſte, and full merites of his paſſion, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it ſhould not nede to do any good workes. This is a foliſh and an vnmete: compariſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe verely of Chriſte agayne, is
<pb facs="tcp:4974:51"/> contrary to fayeth and good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes. For they glorifye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> merittes of Chriſtes paſſion, when the offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe of him agayne is greate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogacion to the ſame. They do as a man that lyghteth a candle, in a bright ſunnye Daye, ſaynge all thoughe the ſunne giueth a light cleare inoughe it of ſelfe: yet it is neceſſarye, and profitable that more lyght be put thereto. But a man maye anſwere ſayeing why do you mocke your ſelfe?</p>
            <p>You haue the bryghte daye in deriſion, as if the ſunne were not ſufficiente wyth out your lyght. So although y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> merites of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes paſſion, are ſufficient to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyue ſynne as the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne is to make a light daye yet, the popiſhe maſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers wyll offer him vp, againe The ſacrifice of the Maſſe, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſynnes (thoughe there be none ſuch) is like a candel ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in a bright ſunny daye, and ſo
<pb facs="tcp:4974:51"/> ſlander the true ſacrifice, to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect. But as we ſe, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the daye, ſo by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowledge of Chriſtes merites we perceyue the goodnes of God towardes vs and fayeth is profitable to vs as a gifte of God, and throughe faith we do good workes, wyllinglie as obediente childerne, but no other good workes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then ſuche as are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded by God.</p>
            <p>We haue nowe declared the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crifice of the Maſſe, to be agaynſt godes commaundement, the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of God and hys glorie. And nowe we wyl proue theſe argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes and aſſertions to be drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of ſcriptur prepoſterouſly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded &amp; playne lyes, which not onely cannot proue and affirme the Maſſe to be a ſacrifice but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo whollye make againſte it It is therfore euidently perceyued that thys popiſhe Maſſe is an horrible abominacion, before God. That
<pb facs="tcp:4974:52"/> they ought to diſpute proue and affirme, by Chriſtes ordinaunces wyth ſure demonſtracions, and plaine textes, of ſcripture, that the Maſſe is a ſacrifice. But there is not one worde or example, that maketh for them, as I haue before declared. They woulde wraſt and turne thys ſayinge (Do thys in my remembraunce) to mayntayne there lyes as who ſay God would theſe wordes, ſhoulde ſignifie to offre, or do ſacrifice. When they muſte be this vnderſtanded, what ſo euer you haue ſeene hearde or done, do it in remembraunce of me but they cannot fynde, in all the ſupper. That Chriſte dyd offre vp ſacrifice. They obiecte, that euerie byſhop choſen of men and appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for men touchinge theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, that belonge to god: doeth of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer gyftes and ſacrifices firſte for hymſelfe and then for the people. Thys aſſercion is of no vertue or
<pb facs="tcp:4974:52"/> ſtrength, for here Saynte Paule ſpeaketh of the prieſtes of the olde lawe, whiche were a figure onely of Chriſt as ye may eaſly perceiue by theſe wordes folowing the ſame texte ſaying. No man muſte take vppon hym, the dignitye of prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hode cxcepte he be called of God as Aaron, and thei which were of the lymage of Aaron. But what is be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>come, of theſe prieſtes? Al thei wer depoſed, and aboliſhed by Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes death, and Chriſte become a prieſt in their ſted, not of the order of Aaron but of Melchiſedeche a man therefore, maye knowe that thys place, of Paule maketh nothynge, for their Maſkinge ſacrifice. And if they wyll haue it to agree, both to the prieſtes, of the olde lawe and newe Teſtamente: they moſt proue whether they be, prieſtes or no. As the name of prieſte mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not a prieſte, but his dedes, like as a begger, named prince, heringe
<pb facs="tcp:4974:53"/> princes to be rulers of people, and countreis. If he claime a people, and countrie which he maye rule; and gouerne ſhal he therfore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a people, and countrie to rule<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> So the popiſhe prieſtes that are prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes in name onlye, hearinge that the prieſtes of the olde lawe did of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſacrifice for ſynnes after godes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te, if they cleime the ſame authorite ſhal thei therefore haue it? But thys is a harde ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge, to ſaye there are no prieſtes nowe in the newe law. Let no man be offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded ther wyth, for vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedlye, there be no prieſtes nowe appointed of God to offer for ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, but euerie chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined of Chriſte, to be a prieſte to praye, to gyue thankes and prayſe to god and to offre vp them ſelues in ſacrifice Saynte Peter ſayeth you are a choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> generacion, a roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all prieſthode and a holly people meaninge therbye al chriſten peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple,
<pb facs="tcp:4974:53"/> as by al chriſtian men. The ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly goſt teacheth the prieſtes of the newe teſtamente, that is to ſaye al chriſten people are of muche more honoure and dignitye then weare the prieſtes of the olde lawe, but none of theſe prieſtes can offre for ſynnes. Yet they obiecte, how can the churche continewe, if we ſhall haue no prieſtes to teach correcte rebuke, and exhort the people. We anſwere that God wyll euer raiſe vp ſome in the congregacion, to do theſe thinges. And Chriſt hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined in al congregacions a ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herde, and preachers, but no maſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers whiche haue brought in to the churche manye errous, by theyr vaine ceremonies and maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge. Alſo where Saynt Paule ſayeth, if we ſynne wyllinglye, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we knowe the trueth there is no ſacrifice lefte to purcheſe vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes theſe papiſtes ga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther of this ſaing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther is no ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fice
<pb facs="tcp:4974:54"/> to helpe them, that ſynne, wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullye, but that there is a ſacrifice yet remayninge for the fayethful, which is their maſſe. They faulſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnderſtande the texte. For S. Paule ſayeth a litle before, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> there is nomore ſacrifice remayning for them whoſe ſynnes are forgyuen al readye, and therefore one place expoundeth another, and plainly declareth, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> there is lefte no more ſacrifice for them, that ſinne of ſet purpoſe or for the that haue obtay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned remiſſion of ſinnes alredie, for Chriſt offered him ſelfe for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyn of thoſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beleue in him, &amp; wil not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him ſelfe againe, for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beleue not, but wilfully remayne in their ſinnes. They obiecte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue an aultar, whereof it is not leaful for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to eate which miniſter in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brenacle, meaninge by thys aul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a heape of ſtones ioyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whiche they call an aulter, but Chriſte hym ſelfe is oure aul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:4974:54"/> wher on we laye oure prayers whiche are oure ſpirituall ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, for no prayeres are accepted of God the father, but by Chriſt. For he ſayth if you aſke my father any thynge in my name, he wyll gyue it you. And ſaynt Paulle expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, his owne ſainge. Let vs offer ſayth he at al times by him a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fice of prayſe whiche is the frutes of our lippes confeſſing his name. We lye therfore, when we call the maſſe our Lords aulter for Chriſt is our onely aulter and S Paule, in all his Epiſtle to the Hebrues, doth knoweledge none other ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fice for ſinnes, but Chriſt once off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe. The papiſtes haue no place of the newe teſtament to make wyth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and therefore, they ſeke helpe of the olde teſtamente. And firſte of the boke of Geneſis they ſaye Melchiſedech. Was the <note place="margin">Geneſ. xiiii.</note> fygure of Chriſte, for he was the prieſte of the hygheſte. And as
<pb facs="tcp:4974:55"/> Dauid ſayeth Chriſte is an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall prieſte after the order of Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedech And therefore he offered breade and wyne vndoubtedly Melchſedech was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> figure of Chriſte but Saynt Paule manifeſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth in what thynges, he was the figure of Chriſt. In the reher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinge of the honours and dignitye of Melchiſedech whiche is that he was an eternall prieſte, and kynge of peace, and ryghtuouſnes. Ther is not one worde, of the offeringe of bread and wyne. They ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not finde in the boke of Geneſis that Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedech dyd ſacrifice to God, but that he offered breade and wyne to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahame, for ſuſtenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as Chriſte offered to vs hys worde. Melchiſedeche broughte breade and wyne and Abrahame payed hym tythes Chriſte after the ſame ſorte gaue vs the ſacrament of his bodye and bloude, but he dyd not offer it to God. The ſcripture ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
<pb facs="tcp:4974:55"/> forth Melechiſedech vnder the fi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gure of an eternal an only prieſte. But the papiſtes appointe othere prieſtes to be Chriſtes viccars af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. If a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhoulde agre wyth them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſte offered to God breade and wyne, yet they cannot proue, that he kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led hym ſelfe in ſacrifice vnder bread, and wyne. Alſo if Chriſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered nothyng but breade &amp; wine: the prieſtes of the olde lawe dyd muche better in kyllinge of liuing creatures, to offer them in ſacrifice The papiſtes cannot, tell what to ſaye, and whan they brynge au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of ſcripture it maketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte them and are confuted wyth there owne ſayinges as one that is ſlayne with his owne wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon. Moreouer they brynge ſuche places of ſcripture as ſpeake of mele and vnleuened breade, as of the breade, that was euer ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinge one the table of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnleuened bread
<pb facs="tcp:4974:56"/> and two loues of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt fruites Al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo where they are iudged holye, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe they offer to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde, an hoſt of bread, &amp; chiefeli thei make great bragges of the ſayinge of Malachias a cleane hoſt is offered to my name in all places, for my name is mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified, among the gentiles. And in what place ſo euer they fynde the offering of breade and wyne, they apply it to ſignifie, the bodely of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feringe of Chriſte in the Maſſe. They beleue that they cannot er, and that theſe dreames, are confir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med by the law, propheſiyng ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by as they did of purgatorie, that wher ſoeuer they ſound this word fiere written in the byble, they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed it to ſignifie purgatory, as they do in thys mater when they can bring no probable reaſon, that Chriſtes bodye ought to be offerd in the Maſſe. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they find any mencion of bloude and other ſacrifices they wraſte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes
<pb facs="tcp:4974:56"/> bodie takynge witneſſe of the olde doctours when thei no better vnderſtande them, then they doo the byble. Nowe we wyll briefely make anſwer to theyr allegations and declare the true maintenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of ſuch places as they alledge to make for theyr purpoſe. And firſte we wyl declare, the ſaiyng of Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chias whereby it maie be perceiued, what the other places ſignifie. He rebuked the I wiſhe prieſtes who gaue them ſelues all together to couetuouſnes, when they ſhoulde haue occupied them ſelues to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer a pure people to the Lorde, and to faſſion there maners after gods commaundementes as the Chapi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter folowinge doeth teſtifye. They oughte to haue taught the people godlines, and all kyndes of vertue but they fed the people w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> foleſhe, and vayne tradicons of men &amp; of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord an vngodly people &amp; foliſhe herted Here is named the
<pb facs="tcp:4974:57"/> filthye breade, the blind, lame, and broken ſacrifice. They maye per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue that the vncleane bread can not ſignifie, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pure bodie of Chriſt that breade and ſacrifice therfore doeth ſignifie, the people as ſaynt Paule ſayeth we are one breade and one bodye, and that he doeth ſeruice to God in preachinge the Goſpell, to make the Gentiles an acceptable ſacrifice to God. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the prieſtes therefore made an vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>godlye and ſinfull people by there doctrine and euill example, God rebuked them and thretneth, that he woulde ordeyne other prieſtes, in theyr ſtead that ſhoulde offer a pure Sacrifice, not only amonge the Iewes, but alſo a monges the gentiles, that is to ſaye, they ſhould enſtructe, the people wyth true godlines and wyth true ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure and worſhip of god. He ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore dyd propheſy of the prieſtes whiche ſhoulde come to offer ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fice
<pb facs="tcp:4974:57"/> of iuſtice, that is to ſay, the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye apoſtles and all other faythful miniſters of gods word. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the people of God whiche is Chriſtes ſpiritual bodie, is brough and offered by their doctrine to God as S. Paule ſayeth I haue ſpouſed the Corinthi, to Chriſte, meaning no other thinge by theſe words, but that by his preaching and miracles, he hath brought and offered in ſacrifice to god the Gentiles whiche were before car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and fleſhly mynded. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">Ro. xii.</note> be exorteth the Romains tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe the mercie of God to gyue theyr bodies to be aliuely facrifice <note place="margin">Iohn. iiii.</note> holly and acceptable to God. The people of God is ſpirituallye the meate which Chriſte deſired moſt and are the twelue loues of ſwete breade, whiche beinge conuerted by the preachinge of the twelue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles doeth continually appere before the face of God. Theſe are
<pb facs="tcp:4974:58"/> the true preiſtes. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they maye bringe to effecte there enterprice, it is mete, that they be holly that is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That they abſteine frome all thynges, that pluckethe them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the true worſhipping of god. This breade is called ſomtyme vndefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. For chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought to walke in the trueth wythout Hypocriſie and fayned lies, and to be anoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with oyle, that is to ſaye wyth the grace of the hollye goſte, true charitie, and mercie this is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true ſence and meaninge of thys texte of ſcripture, declared and proued by other plaſes of ſcripture. But the papiſtes thoughe they alledge the doctors yet they can proue the meaning &amp; vnderſtanding of this text by no place of al the ſcripture Beade in the ſcripture betokneth the word of God. For Chriſt ſaith, man doth not lyue onely by bread but euery word y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> procedeth, from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouth of god The prieſts ought
<pb facs="tcp:4974:58"/> ſincerly to miniſter this breade to the people, and in thys ſignificaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſpirituall bread is not a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> adminiſtracion of the word, &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſtres of god. This is the true manna &amp; angelles fode which was giuen to men, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be their ſuſtenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. By theſe thynges a man may eaſly perceiue what offeringe the Apoſtles and true prieſtes made. Vndoubtly a faithful people who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they brought to god with holſome doctrine, but they offered not the natural bodie of Chriſt after the opinion of theſe fleſhly minded papiſtes, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were done to crucify chriſt againe. Thei beleue Daniel his ſaying maketh muche for there purpoſe where he ſayth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their daylie ſacrifice, called in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhoulde ceaſe for aliene, by this they vnderſtand their Dayly ſacrifice. The Maſſe that nowe beginneth to ceaſe this application is falſely deuiſed. For
<pb facs="tcp:4974:59"/> the ſacrifice that Daniel ſpeake of was offered eueri day at two ſeue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ral <note place="margin">Exod, xxix.</note> times which was in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morning and euening, &amp; that ſacrifice with other I wyſhe ſacrifices ceaſſed when Chriſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> only true ſacrifice offered himſelfe on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aulter of the croſſe. You may therfore eaſly per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrifice of the mas, for it is not done, both in the morning &amp; theuening, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other was. and Euſebius ſaith our lords ſupper vnder ſome byſhopes was miniſtred but once or twyſe, in the yere, the hiſtory of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dayelie ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, that Daniel ſpeaketh of, was fulfilled vnder Antiochus the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran, for in hys tyme there was no ſacrifice offered in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> temple of god for the ſpace of thre or foure yeres In dede this is true. Antiochus, was the figure of Antichriſte for he toke a waye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true worſhiping and honour of god. And truſte in god, &amp; faith is extinguiſhed, when 5<pb facs="tcp:4974:59"/> men truſte more, in theyr owne power &amp; workes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in gods grace they haue certayne other dreames and aſſertions but of no vertue or ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth. One is, thei ſay the eaſter lambe was offered euerie yere, ſo Chriſte the true Eaſter Lambe ought to be offered ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tymes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be more foliſhe then this Argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. For the eaſter la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be, was not offred for ſinnes but only was ſlayne and eaten in remenbraunce of the deliuerau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the Iſraelits out of Egipte. But nowe the papi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes offer for ſinnes the ſacrifice of the maſſe. For they are not conten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thonly reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Other ſacrifices wer of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fered agayne, for they were vnper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte, but Chriſt being a perfecte &amp; ſufficient ſacrifice ought to be offe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red once, for euer. Thei obiect that wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the preachers &amp; doctours did ſacrifice at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> election of Paul &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſted, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holly goſt fayed &amp;c. the greke
<pb facs="tcp:4974:60"/> word y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlate to ſignifie to do ſacrifice, hath in this place y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it hath in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. xiii. Cha. to the Romaines, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is to miniſter as a <note place="margin">Ro. xiii.</note> magiſtrate in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> como<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth. And therfore after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tranſlacion of the papiſtes euerie maieſtrate is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preiſt. But thei y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wilbe eſtemed, to be wittie and learned amongeſte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reaſon after this maner when Chriſt offered himſelfe) the church alſo which is his ſpowſe, may offer hym for ſynnes in the Maſſe. For Chriſt &amp; hys church ſo agree and ſo conſente together. That what ſo euer the one doth the other agre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth to the ſame. But thys is a lye. For if Chriſte died for vs, then the church muſt do the ſame. Chriſt is the bread &amp; highe prieſte. Ergo we are the bread and highe prieſt alſo. Chriſte was offered ſay they wyth payne, and ſufferinge of the bodie. Ergo he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be offered &amp; ſuffer not. He was once a ſacrifice, ergo he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:4974:60"/> be a ſacrifice againe. But this ther talke is vayne and foleſhe. For we ſeke not what Chriſt might do but what he dyd. And what the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture teacheth. Alſo they obiecte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is better to gyue, then to take. In ſacrifice we giue, &amp; in our Lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des ſupper we take it is therefore better to offer. But let them firſt proue who gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> authoritie to do ſacrifice after thys man. It is better to be a ſauioure the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and ſeruante. Therfore as it is a greate blaſphemie, a man to ſaye he is a god, and ſauiour, ſo it is great blaſphemy y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſinners ſhall go about to offer Chriſt for remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſinnes. So thus it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>eth to paſſe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the more thei defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d their er<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rourres y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more vngodli thei ſhew the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues againſte Gods maieſtie Some of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> papiſtes doubt not to ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſin dayly, therfore dayely ſacrifice is neceſſary. And they ſay Chriſt toke away the ſin paſt only
<pb facs="tcp:4974:61"/> which is called original ſin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſatiſfacion for other ſinnes, muſte be made other wiſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is by workes and ſacrifices And thei put to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other thinges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> differ ſo much from the doctrine of fayth as any chriſten ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hearing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may eaſly perceiue. For the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that Chriſte is neither God nor a true ſauiour. Now we haue decla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red, what the Maſſe is. Not a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for ſinnes but an horible a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before God. Al Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought therfore to ſhone and fle frome it and tourn to the true vſe of oure Lordes Supper accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge to hys moſte holy or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaunce. To whome be honoure and glorie for euer</p>
            <closer>AMEN</closer>
            <trailer>Fines</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:4974:61"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
